<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Loyalty amongst rebels the true royalist, or, Hushay the Archite, a happy counsellour in King David's greatest danger / written by Edward Wolley ...</title>
            <author>Wolley, Edward, 1603-1684.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1662</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 190 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 112 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66831</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3266</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R31822</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12266722</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12266722</idno>
            <idno type="VID">58102</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66831)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 58102)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1516:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Loyalty amongst rebels the true royalist, or, Hushay the Archite, a happy counsellour in King David's greatest danger / written by Edward Wolley ...</title>
                  <author>Wolley, Edward, 1603-1684.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[38], 180, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Williams ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1662.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Second part has title: The parallel betwixt King Charles the II, King of England and Lewis the IV, the French king.</note>
                  <note>Errata sheet bound at end.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: print showthrough with loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Monarchy.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:58102:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of a male figure in a torn coat at the bottom of a hill</figDesc>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>2:</hi> Sam: <hi>15:</hi> vers the <hi>32</hi>
                     </bibl> Behold Hushai the Archite came to meet the King with his coat rent and earth upon his head</q>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:58102:1"/>
            <p>Loyalty amongſt REBELS. The True ROYALIST, Or HUSHAY the Archite. A happy Counſellour in King's DAVID'S Greateſt <hi>Danger.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Say unto Abſalon I will be thy ſervant O King.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 Sam. 15.34.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>I Counſel thee to keep the Kings Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and that in Regard of the Oath of God.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Eccleſ. 8.2.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Written by EDWARD WOLLEY D.D. and Chaplain in Ordinary to his Sacred Majeſty King CHARLES the II.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Iohn Williams,</hi> at the ſigne of the <hi>Crown</hi> in <hi>S. Paul</hi>'s Churchyard. 1662.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:58102:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:58102:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable <hi>JOHN</hi> Baron <hi>Grenvil</hi> of <hi>Kilkhampton</hi> and <hi>Biddi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> Viſcount <hi>Grenvil</hi> of <hi>Landſ-Down</hi> and Earle of <hi>Bathe, Groome</hi> of the <hi>Stool,</hi> and firſt <hi>Gentleman</hi> of the <hi>Bed-Chamber,</hi> Lord <hi>Warden</hi> of the <hi>Stanneryes,</hi> Lord <hi>Lieutenant</hi> of the County of <hi>Cornwall;</hi> and High <hi>Steward</hi> of the <hi>Dutchy</hi> and <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour</hi> of his Majeſties <hi>Town; Iſland, Fort</hi> and <hi>Caſtle</hi> of the Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of <hi>Plimouth.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have had the honour and happines to know
<pb facs="tcp:58102:3"/>you from your tender years, and have diſcerned your cordial affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, to ſerve the <hi>Church,</hi> as an obedient Sonne; your <hi>Prince,</hi> as a moſt Loyal Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; &amp; your <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:58102:3"/>as a moſt faithful Patriot. And as <hi>Pompey</hi> (when but a youth) to expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience your For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, &amp; fidelity to the Crown, and (without injury or flattery) it may, in ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree,
<pb facs="tcp:58102:4"/>be ſaid of you, as <hi>Plutarch</hi> writes of that No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Roman, Is etiamnum adole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcens, totum ſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctioni Syllanae ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dixit; cumque nec Magiſtratus, nec Senator eſſet, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnum ex Italiâ
<pb facs="tcp:58102:4"/>contraxit exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum.</hi> That you were a very early Commander in your youth, and thoſe four terrible wounds, which you received in the fight at <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berry; three in your head, and one
<pb facs="tcp:58102:5"/>in your arm:</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue thoſe marks and cicatrices, which, as honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable badges of loyalty, will bear you company to your Grave. It was a queſtion once ſtarted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>Aſcanius</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:58102:5"/>by <hi>Andromache:</hi> whether he was like his Father <hi>Aeneas</hi> or his Vncle <hi>Hector,</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Ecquid in antiquam vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutem animoſque viriles</l>
               <l>Et Pater Aeneas, &amp; a vunculus excitat Hector?</l>
               <l>Andromache in Virgil:</l>
               <l>Aeneid de Aſcanio.</l>
            </q>
            <p>But there is not
<pb facs="tcp:58102:6"/>any need of ſuch a queſtion concerning your Lordſhip, in whom the varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of your Noble <hi>Anceſtors</hi> ſeem to concenter: So that the pietie of <hi>Richardus de Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nâ Villâ,</hi> who
<pb facs="tcp:58102:6"/>founded the <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey of Neath in Glamorgan-shire,</hi> in the fourth year of the raigne of <hi>King William Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fus,</hi> liveth in you. The courage of <hi>Sir Richard Gren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil,</hi> your great Grandfather who
<pb facs="tcp:58102:7"/>commanded the Rear-Admiral, a Ship called the <hi>Revenge;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he ſo gallantly behaved himſelf, that in a deſperate fight at Sea with the Spaniards, he ſunk &amp; deſtroyed infinite numbers
<pb facs="tcp:58102:7"/>of <hi>Qu. Elizabeths enemies,</hi> when o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers made all the ſail they could to avoid the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.) And the loyalty and great worth of <hi>Sir Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill Grenvill</hi> ſeem as thriving ſeeds to grow up, and
<pb facs="tcp:58102:8"/>flourish in you. And it will be an honour and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs to your Lordship, to be not onely a Son and Heire of his Name &amp; loynes, but of his virtues; who ſo loved the <hi>Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,
<pb facs="tcp:58102:8"/>that in perſon he guarded the late Lord Archbishop of Canterbury</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the fury of the tumultuous Rabbles in all commotions and Rebellions; either of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> (in the
<pb facs="tcp:58102:9"/>late <hi>bleſſed Kings Raign,</hi>) he mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted the dutie of a Loyal Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, and of a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Commander, at the fight at <hi>Stratton;</hi> he was ſucceſsful againſt the enemie, with a handful of men;
<pb facs="tcp:58102:9"/>And at the fight at <hi>Lands-downe;</hi> like another <hi>Epa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minondas,</hi> though he loſt his life, he got the Victory: <hi>Et cum ſentiret vulnus eſſe lethale, non prius ferrum eduxit, quam au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſet Thebanos
<pb facs="tcp:58102:10"/>viciſſe, tum ſatis inquit, vixi, invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus enim morior.</hi> To encourage his Souldiers; he fought with blee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding wounds, and finding that his countrey men, like Gallant <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bans,</hi> won the day:
<pb facs="tcp:58102:10"/>
               <hi>animam efflavit;</hi> he fell gloriouſly into the boſome of true honour &amp; renown: Theſe exemplars of vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue have (doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs) attracted your Reſolutions to imitation of your Anceſtors,
<pb facs="tcp:58102:11"/>and have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed your affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions with true and right princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Nobleneſs and honour. But that which ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders you moſt lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vely to all who know your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, is that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable
<pb facs="tcp:58102:11"/>ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, which by your prudence, fidelity, ſecre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and courage: was tranſacted &amp; effected, together with the <hi>Duke of Albemarle,</hi> and his brother the <hi>Lord Bishop of
<pb facs="tcp:58102:12"/>Hereford:</hi> in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties</hi> Reſtaura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth <hi>three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes</hi> happy. This is the chiefeſt loadſtone &amp; mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, that makes me addreſs to your Lordship
<pb facs="tcp:58102:12"/>for patronage and protection in this argument, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I endeavour to prove; that <hi>truth</hi> may be in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany with <hi>Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors,</hi> and <hi>Loyalty</hi> amongſt <hi>Rebels,</hi> as <hi>Hushai the Archite</hi> who was
<pb facs="tcp:58102:13"/>
               <hi>King Davids</hi> beſt friend, and moſt faithful ſubject in his greateſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. It is true; many worthyes did attend his <hi>Majeſties Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> in pinching extremityes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad for many
<pb facs="tcp:58102:13"/>years, and many thouſand loyal Subjects of the <hi>three Kingdomes</hi> indured inſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portable miſeries from uſurping &amp; bloody Wolves at home, and the <hi>ſtings</hi> of a ſort of <hi>Trepanning creep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:58102:14"/>Serpants,</hi> (as equally vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous as dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous) hardly to be avoided. Theſe true <hi>Royaliſts</hi> were (on all occaſions) active in their perſons, in their counſels, in their relations, &amp; their
<pb facs="tcp:58102:14"/>friends in their purſes, and their prayers, and by all wayes and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſts, to promote his <hi>Majeſties Reſtauration.</hi> But your <hi>Lordship</hi> (as a more ſignal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of much happineſs) hath
<pb facs="tcp:58102:15"/>received gracious <hi>markes</hi> of Noble truſt, honour and favour, from his <hi>Majesty;</hi> &amp; the thanks of all <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> in the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes</hi> Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> which will prove a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py
<pb facs="tcp:58102:15"/>
               <hi>record</hi> of your honour to poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and bleſſed for ever be thoſe hands and hearts, who have contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted much, or caſt in, if but a mite, to that bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed work. There is another ſmall
<pb facs="tcp:58102:16"/>&amp; tender <hi>branch,</hi> which budded ſeaſonably about <hi>ſeven years</hi> ſince, and appeared in the <hi>Kingdom;</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the complexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and colour of a <hi>Tranſlation</hi> in the caſe and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel of <hi>Lewis</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:58102:16"/>the <hi>fourth</hi> the <hi>French King.</hi> This, firſt went abroad to keep alive thoſe loyal ſparks, which lay-under the aſhes of <hi>Cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> and <hi>Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> in the year 1654. &amp; meeting with curteous
<pb facs="tcp:58102:17"/>tinder, it took fire, and inflamed many affections towards the <hi>King.</hi> This ſmall piece was reprinted eight moneths before his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties</hi> return to <hi>England;</hi> and it proved ſo proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous,
<pb facs="tcp:58102:17"/>that ſome thouſand copies were diſperſed &amp; vented in fourty houres. And then it grew ſuddenly a publick diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe in the City and Countrey <hi>(videlicet:)</hi> the <hi>Kings</hi> Caſe in the
<pb facs="tcp:58102:18"/>Parallel of <hi>Lewis the fourth</hi> of <hi>France:</hi> This Branch leans on your Lordships Patronage and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, &amp; is added to this diſcourſe, to perpetuate all Subjects reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in their alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance
<pb facs="tcp:58102:18"/>to their <hi>Princes,</hi> and as a part of juſtice and merit, that his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours nay be diſcerned, who gave it life, &amp; firſt fixed and planted it in <hi>England,</hi> and ſo not to be any longer fathered
<pb facs="tcp:58102:19"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:58102:19"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:58102:20"/>on adopted au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors.<note n="*" place="margin">Tulit alter honores. <hi>Virgil.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>My Lord,</hi> I shall not afflict your Lordship with any further preſent trouble; but wishing the increaſe of happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and honour; dayly to redound on your Lordſhip
<pb facs="tcp:58102:20"/>and your enobled family. I cordially ſubſcribe my Self; (<hi>My ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured Lord,</hi>)</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Lordſhips faithfully obliged Servant</hi> EDWARD WOLLEY, D.D.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:58102:21"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:58102:21"/>
            <head>LOYALTY AMONGST REBELS The true Royaliſt OR <hi>Hushai</hi> the <hi>Archite</hi> A happy Councellour in King <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> greateſt danger.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Ominion and Soveraigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, the higheſt truſt, and moſt illuſtrious gift that<note n="a" place="margin">Quid ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes quam unum pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſse pluribus? leges &amp; juſſa ponere? maria terras. Pacem &amp; bella mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rari? I. Lips. ad Reges imperat. Principes, Epiſt. dedica. Polit.</note> God beſtoweth on his creature man, for what degree can be more ſublime then for one to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:58102:22"/>be ſupream; and to command ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thouſands: to make lawes, and to impoſe decrees that ſhall force o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience. And having an influence on mens lives, liberties, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes; to hold the raines of govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in all affaires, both by ſea and land, and by the rights of an unlimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted juſt prerogative to have power to regulate and moderate the viciſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of Peace and War: and by grant and Commiſſion from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven<hi rend="sup">b</hi> to ſuperintend, and to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe an imperial and ſoveraign pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in all concernments;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.5.</note> whether Eccleſiaſtical, Civil or Martial: this dignity only ſuites and ſeemes fit for ſome terreſtrial diety,<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Pſal, 82.6.</hi> Dixi dii eſtis. <hi>Proverb. 8.15.</hi> Per me Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges regnant.</note> and therefore may juſtly expect and challenge a Perſon of Greateſt worth and moſt compleat capacities; &amp; the rather be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ſtate of<note n="d" place="margin">K <hi>Iames</hi> duty of a. K. in his Royal office. p. 2.</note> Monarchy is the ſupreameſt thing upon earth. And Kings are not only Gods Lievte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants upon earth, but by God himſelf
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:58102:22"/>they are called Gods, whom they much reſemble in ſeveral Attributes, of Wiſdome, Power, juſtice, Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and the like. Thus Kings as mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Gods create or deſtroy; make or unmake at pleaſure, give life or ſend death to their ſubjects, are judges o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all, &amp; owe accompt to none but God, they humble or advance them at their pleaſure; and as Arithmeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians placing their figures, cauſe their ſubjects (at their pleaſure) to ſignifie a greater or ſmaller number, or to be as meer cyphers, that ſhall be utterly uſeleſſe and inſignificant. To this ſupream order of mortals, to Kings and ſoveraign Princes, is due the affection of the Soul and the ſervice of the body from all their ſubjects. And from this principle and root of obedience ſprings up the branches of fidelity, Allegiance and Loyalty; which is to be paid and performed to lawful Kings and Princes, from all their ſubjects; none
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:58102:23"/>but ſeditious and traiterous ſpirits dare aſſert the contrary; and this la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Age hath too much been poyſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with ſuch diſtillations and dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous untruths: which, though they produced many horrid miſchiefs and monſters, (the ugly common births of Rebellion and Treaſon,) are now unmasked and more clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcerned, by the beames of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience; and a more perſpicuous light which hath in a great propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion diſperſed thoſe miſts and foggs that engendred and begat ſo many prodigious and horrid effects to a gracious<note n="*" place="margin">K. Charles the firſt the royal martyr.</note> King, and a moſt unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py and miſerable People.<note n="†" place="margin">A Civil war and confuſion and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractions of almoſt twenty yeares.</note> So then there needs no diſpute nor directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Subjects to there duty; ſeeing all are involved to the rules of obedience, by the lawes of God and man, but it may be of ſome concernment to many, who love the company and comfort of a good conſcience as Chriſtians, and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:58102:23"/>to others, who thirſt after nothing more, then true honour and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, as men or ſubjects, to make a privy ſearch into their own ſoules, and ſo to bring there actions words and affections to the touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone of truth, whereby they may finde there failings from, or their performance in, their loyal duties to wards their Soveraign; and ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandoning all excuſes, and wave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all unjuſt pretences, make out a happy ſatisfaction to themſelves: though not to others, who either too ſupercilious, as <hi>Cato,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Cato uti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſis ſtoica diſciplina ſeverus; nudis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terdum pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibus, bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vique toga in Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat. Plut. Timon A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenienſis temporibus Peloponia ci belli, in humanus, ab Atheni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enſibus <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, appellatus quaſi genus hominum infenſum fuerit. Caro. Stepha.</note> or to rigid as <hi>Timon</hi> the <hi>Athenian,</hi> undiſcreetly or uncharitably cenſure all mens actions but their own, in this ſcruti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niny, that ſo neerly concerns ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and conſcience: the proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings ought to be impartial, and the examination ſtrickt, becauſe the concernment is ſo conſiderable, and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:58102:24"/>in this particular, neither politick rules, great and more eminent ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, nor glorious and advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious ſucceſſes, are to guide or gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie affections, or to blindfold and captivete reaſon; but an untainted judgement, ſetled and fixed on true principles of honour and Chriſtian ſincerity, is the trueſt light in ſuch a dark and dangerous path; where ſelf intereſt, flattery, opinion, hope, fear, and many ſuch inherent compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions are induſtrious to divert good inclinations, and to exchange them from the love of virtue and truth. As to the rules of humain politicks (as muſh-rooms in a night) they are conceived in ſecrecy of Councels; and have their birth and appear in the day: and thoſe maximes are as alterable as the wind, which in an inſtant moveth from one point to another of the card or compaſs. As to examples, though never ſo great or numerous they are not to ſway,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:58102:24"/>a noble minde from what is truly honorable, nor a good Chriſtian from any point or tenet that is reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious and juſt; and as to ſucceſſes, though never ſo proſperous, they ought not to move or prevail with a generous and pious ſpirit, to make him vicious, hyprocritical or falſe. For if honour be rather in the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions or eſtimations of others, then in our ſelves rather in merit &amp; truth, then titles and forced Ceremonies; and victory unjuſtly or more cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly and obſcurely gotten, brings leſs of true renown: how ingrate muſt ſucceſſes to riches, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement to great places be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out an honourable atchievement, &amp; juſt acquiſition. Theſe conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſtated, a loyal perſon may more eaſily ſift himſelf, and after ſo many difficulties and tryals of a civil war, enter more ſecurely into the ſecrets of his own ſoul; and their removing all ſcruples, may more cleerly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:58102:25"/>how faithfully and ſincerely he hath adhered too, or how per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidiouſly and falſly he hath apoſtated and fallen from his duty to God and to his King. It is true the world is too full of excuſes and apologies, each perſon (clad with the reſolutions of ſelf intereſt, either too much magnifying his owne merits, or too much extenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating his own crimes and errors) is ſick of ſelf love. And as <hi>Minerva</hi> blowing a Flagellet or pipe puffed up her cheeks though to a deformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: many ſwell and grow big with the breath of ſelf opinion, and though their wayes &amp; workes have been never ſo diſſonant or oppoſite to honour, reaſon or truth; Yet in a Thraſonical humour, or Phariſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal pride, they cry up and juſtifie all their own proceedings, with all the circumſtances of their dictates and deſignes, and at the ſame time are ready to decry and detract from
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:58102:25"/>others: though never ſo ſquare in their actions and ſincere and candid in all their reſolutions. Seeing then that <hi>Philautia,</hi> ſelf love and adulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſo eaſily, ſuddenly, and pleaſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſurpriſeth mens phanſies, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupteth their judgements, captiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth reaſon: and in fine enſlaveth the ſoul, it may well become all who are truely enamored with virtue, honour, juſtice and the hopes of a good report, or (to mount a ſtep higher) to love the peace and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility of a calm and unſpotted con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, in this nice point, care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to ſubmit there ſenſes to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and the ſtrength of reaſon, to the force and power of godlineſſe, which is the beſt preſervative of the ſoul in all trials and more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined probations.</p>
            <p>And it is Piety that is the touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone that diſcovereth the mettall whether it be true or falſe; It is the ſcale that ballanceth every word
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:58102:26"/>and action, and determineth them either weighty or light. This as the rudder of the Ship governeth, as the anchor it holdeth, as the Pilot it directeth, and as the keile ſwim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in the bottom of the angry waves, it ſecureth and ſupporteth all the ſuperſtructure of the float<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing artificial Caſtle, that overgli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth and ſurmounteth the lofty billowes of the Ocean. Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is the daughter of Piety, which (grounded on the principles of truth, and a good cauſe,) encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth men to be divinely affected to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, and loyally reſolved to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their Prince. It is probable in this great revolution and ſtupen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious viciſſitude of government, the ſtreames of the ſubjects affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, returning paſſionately to their King, and to monarchy, that all, or at leaſt the greateſt number of the people of the three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes may pleade a co-operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:58102:26"/>or a concurrency in this miraculous change. And as the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers in the vineyard to boaſt and proclaim, that they have not only ſuffered and ſweat, but even born the brunt and bickerment of the day: others may perhaps challenge to themſelves the merit, not only of pardon and amneſty, but of thanks, grace and favour; becauſe they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared ſerviceable at the laſt hour: and doubtleſs royal bounty will not deny them the wages of their loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty, if their return to their Prince be cordial and ſincere. But the caſe of <hi>Huſhai</hi> the <hi>Archite</hi> ſtated rightly, may like a bright <hi>Beacon</hi> ſet on fire, and (flaming on ſome high Mountain,) give an Alarum, and luſter, to the amazement of all ſpectators. In this preſident of <hi>Huſhai,</hi> a loyal ſubject may ſee the warrant, the reaſons, the matter, the manner, and the truths of his duty, being ſuch an example in the King,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:58102:27"/>who imployed him in the perſon, who was commanded and truſted, and for the eminency and concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the ſervice, wherein he was employed, that hardly and humain or holy hiſtory can parallel the like, and all theſe circumſtances conduce much to guide the Prince to his royal care, whom to truſt or em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy, and as equally concerns the the ſubjects and people how to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of themſelves even in their greateſt dangers of their lives and fortunes, towards their King and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign. This hath been the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of many gallant and loyal ſoules, who not only in their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal valour, but in all their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivances, and councels, have made it their choiceſt intereſt, as equally near as the ſaving of their ſoules, to hold up the honour of the crown withall its juſt rites and preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, ever ſince the firſt commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and troubles of the late war,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:58102:27"/>or that the late formidable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion had ſo intoxicated and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witched the giddy humours of the People of his Majeſties three king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes; and as perſons of theſe affections, reſolutions and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples were led and fixed to their Prince, ſo, a zealous duty to the Church of <hi>England</hi> their mother, wrought their perſwaſions, to a careful preſervation of that truth and religion; which the moſt learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and moſt judicious ſober Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans hold fourth, for, both doctrine and diſcipline to be the pureſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, the beſt form of ſerving God; and to come neareſt to the pious practiſe of the primitive Chriſtians: and though in the three Kingdomes, it was forced like a Dove to the clefts of the Rocks, to fly into upper chambers, private Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſets, or ſecret corners, yet the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God, the ſaving of Soules, the beauty of Sion, was (ever du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:58102:28"/>the violence of the perſecution) ſo precious, that the Church of <hi>England</hi> found dutiful children, and couragious Sons and Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in her blackeſt Afflictions. And as the Ark had the protection of a Royal Patron and nurſing Father abroad for many years,<note place="margin">K. Charles the 2.</note> ſo it was ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported and preſerved by the duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful hands and hearts of many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of the three Kingdomes, whoſe very ſoules did pray and long for nothing more then his Majeſties joyful Reſtoration, and that the Ark might return happily with him. And now (not to looſe the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) a review may be more Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuinely taken, and a ſtricter exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation made in <hi>Huſhai</hi> the <hi>Archites</hi> great and wiſe undertakings, and his happy and high performances and ſucceſſes, both to the Church, the Crown and the Kingdome of <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Iſrael,</hi> for all, who made bonefires, cauſed Bells to ring, and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:58102:28"/>with other external circumſtances made Heaven and Earth to rejoice with chearful and loud acclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: were not <hi>Iſraelites</hi> indeed, like <hi>Nathaniel,</hi> or wiſe and couragious and loyal <hi>Huſhai:</hi> it may be believed that many who had wide throats and made loud vociferations at his Majeſties return, had but narrow affections; and tis poſſible, that guilt or fear, or danger, may force a compliancy, where the ſtream was ſo ſtrangely turned, and ran as a mighty Tide or torrent with ſuch irreſiſtable violence. Therefore <hi>Huſhai's</hi> wiſdome and loyalty, and the conduct of his affaires (in ſo dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous a Cryſis and juncture of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremities,) may prove a more happy Patern for all ages, and like <hi>Ariad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi> clue of Silk, direct all worthy ſubjects, like <hi>Theſeus,</hi> more proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly to encounter the minotaure or monſter of Rebellion; and having ſlain that bloudy and ſavage beaſt
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:58102:29"/>more ſecurely to return out of the labyrinth and interrigues of ſuch Helliſh deluſion; in the company of true honour, triumph and victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: It is not to be doubted but ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny pretend to this noble <hi>Iſraelites</hi> worth and merits, who if rightly reflected on; know well (as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcious to themſelves) that either they have forfeited their Faith and Allegiance ever ſince the original commencement of the late civil warrs, or in an over activity in their Rebellious endeavours, have done moſt horrid injuries to their King and Country, or in a tepid fit of Newtrality, have been luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warm; and baſely complacent to both parties, or elſe in a degree yet more ignoble and fordid, having <hi>(animas venales)</hi> vendible and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenary ſpirits, have entertained the wages of iniquity, and under the guiſe and pretence of loyal ſubjects and faithful Patriots have betrayed
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:58102:29"/>and deſtroyed the Prince and his People, or (if there can be any thing worſe) there is a brood and genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of pretenders, to the beſt and moſt loyal ſervices, becauſe they at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended in the Navie, that wafted &amp; refluctuated the King into <hi>England;</hi> that they had adventured to <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da,</hi> to <hi>Bruſſels</hi> to <hi>Holland,</hi> to <hi>France,</hi> to <hi>Germany,</hi> that they had been active at home, and dutiful abroad, and had contrived and contributed moſt, both in their perſons and purſes, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his Majeſties Reſtauration.</p>
            <p>And it were an unkindneſſe, if not a crime to derogate from ſuch pretenſive merits: but the ſting that cauſeth a ſore ſwelling, is that theſe new brooms (returned to loyalty,) ſweep all ſo clean, that they leave no work, not the leaſt Atome of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour in this high concern to thoſe nobler ſpirits, who never forfeited their fidelity to their King; but as <hi>Huſhai</hi> ever walked by the influence
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:58102:30"/>of his Majeſties commiſſion or commands, and in all conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, whether active or paſſive, in the concerns of their Faith and Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, never ſwerved, nor ſo much as warped from their Native obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, or from the rules and dictates of Honour and a good Conſcience. This great <hi>Hero</hi> and exemplar of his fidelity to his Prince, is recorded in the Sacred book of God, and thence recommended to all ſubjects, of all ages, &amp; of all Kingdomes, as a lively pattern to direct them in their duty and ſervice towards their Soveraign; and in many excellencies he is hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly imitable, for the holy Hiſtorian tells the world,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 15.</note> that this loyal <hi>Iſraelite,</hi> unſummon'd, unſent for, no ſooner heard the news of the Kings ſad condition, that <hi>Abſolon</hi> was unnaturally turn'd Traitor againſt his Father. and the people in Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion againſt their King, but inſtantly this great worthy marcheth after his
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:58102:30"/>Prince, and finding him on the top of the Mount, where he worſhiped God, he attended his Soveraign Lord with diligence and haſte, though his ſad poſture preſented the Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and ſorrow of his ſoul, (for his coat was rent, and his head was co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered with earth,) and what poſture could better become a loyal heart, then what cleerly expreſſed grief, or indignation, to ſee or hear of a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedient Son perſecuting a loving Father, or a ſtubborn deluded peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple infatuated into a high and hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid Rebellion: but <hi>Huſhai</hi> was nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtartled at his Princes dangerous condition, nor conſulted for his own ſafety, nor was catched with flattery and the large promiſes of the Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors oyle and ſmooth tongue, nor did he dread or ſtand amazed, at the oraculous Counſells of <hi>Achitophel,</hi> (the grand politician,) but his Native duty conducts him ſpeedily to wait on his Prince; and true and unſpot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:58102:31"/>loyallty &amp; allegiance directing him in his march, without any doubts or diſputes, laying his life at his Maſters feet; he in an inſtant beſpeaks himſelf a perfect Royaliſt, and ſo with his life, friends, and fortune ready to obey whatever commands the King thinks fit to impoſe upon him. Some noble Heathens have left to the world famous examples of their love and loyalty to their Princes: and to the ſhame and diſhonour of many infamous Chriſtians, have exceeded them for their fidelity and true allegiance. <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Hephaeſtion unut ex Alex. mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni ducibus; quem ille cum Crate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro ita conte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rebaiut hunc quidem <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>Hepha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionem vero <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>appellaret Plutarch. in vita Alexandri.</note> hath recorded <hi>Hephaeſtion,</hi> (to the memory of his immortal honour,) that he paſſionately loved and eſteemed the perſon of <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> the great, and in his diſcourſe with <hi>Craterus,</hi> the Conquerour told him that <hi>Hephaeſtion</hi> did not only love him as a King, but did moſt affectionately honour him as <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander.</hi> And it was a royal mark and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:58102:31"/>diſtinction of <hi>Alexanders</hi> own creat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to ſtile <hi>Craterus</hi> a lover of the King, but <hi>Hephaeſton</hi> a lover and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirer of <hi>Alexander,</hi> and it ſeems his duty to his Prince, as it received bounty from his Soveraign whiles he lived, was rewarded with high honour when he was dead, for the ſame Author affirmes, that this no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Emperour, in a grateful memory to ſo faithful a ſubject, and ſo cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agious a commander, magnificently expended more then twelve thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Talents upon his exequies and Funerals. There is ſuch ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther paſſage of <hi>Clitus</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Clitus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter pracipu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>os Alexan. Maced. familiares eidemque chariſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus quod filius eſset<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutricis illi us, tum quod ab illo in vitae diſcrimine fuiſſet ſervatus: hunc in convivio liberius in Perſicos mores invectum, Rex temulentus ſpiculo trajecit, cujus facti poſtridie tanta cepit paenitentia diſcuſsa jam ebrietate ut totum triduum à cibo abſtinue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, decreveritque omuino inedia ſibi mortem conciſsere ac amicum optime de ſe meritum ad inferos perſequi &amp; ſumptuoſo cumfunere ſepelivit. Plutarc. in vita Alexandri.</note> who having been <hi>Alexanders</hi> nurcesſon, and in his perſon and Relations moſt ſerviceable to the King in many of his greateſt dangers. The Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour advanced him to great favours
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:58102:32"/>and enriched him with Princely mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificency: and when a <hi>Perſian</hi> intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate exceſſe and debauchery had drown'd the Kings reaſon, and had raiſed a tempeſt in his paſſions; ſo that in his fury with a javelin he had ſlain his favourite: yet this ſad acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent ſo deeply affected the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, when he had recovered his confounded reaſon, that he appeared to be overwhelmed in a gulf of ſhame and ſorrow, and ſo giving rules for his own pennance, obliged himſelf to a hard duty; hence de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termining and decreeing, that his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperance ſhould be rewarded with penury, and that he who had ſo ignobly abuſed plenty, and in ſuch extravagant luxury ſlain his friend, ſhould juſtly dye and periſh for want of food: hereby the King propoſed a more ſpeedy death to himſelf, that he might more ſuddenly follow the Ghoſt of <hi>Clytus</hi> to the imagined ſhades below. Such a character of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:58102:32"/>true worth and loyalty, <hi>Darius</hi> gave of his dear <hi>Zophyrus,</hi> who waging warr and beſieging the vaſt City of <hi>Babylon,</hi> (but without ſucceſſe or victory,) truſted the poſſibilities of the effecting of that deſign to the fidelity, courage and wiſdome of faithfull <hi>Zophyrus,</hi> who the better to diſguiſe himſelf and to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh the conqueſt with grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſafety to his perſon, and more ſecure ſucceſſe to his So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign, disfigured his face to a high deformity, and having permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his ears, his<note n="†" place="margin">Nobilis Perſa ipſe ſibi naſum, aures &amp; la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bia amputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit &amp; ita Babylonas, quaſi tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuga ſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulit con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querens de crudelitate ſui Regis; receptus e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitur a Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byloniis &amp; dux belli conſtitutus, urbem Dario tradidit, unde Darius ſolebat di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere; ſe Zophyrum malle integrum quam viginti capere Babylonas, Herod. lib. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> lips, and his noſe to be cut off (as pretended by a <hi>Perſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> barbarous cruelty,) in this po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture he adreſſed to the <hi>Babylonians,</hi> as an abuſed and tortured <hi>Perſian</hi> fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitive, where being received and advanced to great truſt and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand as a General of their Army,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:58102:33"/>by his prudence and valour ſubdued <hi>Babylon,</hi> and delivered the City to his own Maſter and Lord; for which ſignal ſervice, <hi>Darius</hi> was wont to ſay familiarly, that he did owe ſo much true honour and reſpect to his dear <hi>Zophyrus,</hi> that he would ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have received him from <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> without any blemiſh or mutila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion then to have twenty Cities ſuch as <hi>Babylon</hi> ſubdued to his imperial Scepter. <hi>Menelaus, Agamemnon,</hi> and <hi>Vliſſes</hi> had great ſervice effected by the fidelity, ingenuity and cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age of <hi>Sinon</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Virgil <hi>2.</hi> Aeneidos.</note>, who like a ſtout da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and ſubtil Greek, inſinuated and inſnared the <hi>Trojans</hi> to their ruine, and ſo effected a happy ſucceſſe, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with much honour and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nown to the Greeks in their long ſiege to <hi>Troy. Marcus Antonius</hi> was a true, faithful and loyal friend to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and when he could do him no longer ſervice in the Imperours life, being ſlain by the conſpirators,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:58102:33"/>he took his royal Robe ſtained with blood, ſtabbed, cut and mang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and making his funeral Orations to the people, fill'd their eyes with tears, their ſouls with ſorrow, and by degrees, drew them to vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive reſolutions to revenge <hi>Caeſars</hi> death;<note place="margin">Plutarch' in vita Bruti.</note> which cauſed <hi>Cymber</hi> and <hi>Brutus</hi> and the chief conſpirators to fly for fear of popular inſurrection &amp; fury againſt the Traitors: the light of theſe Pagan &amp; Heathen examples, is not ſo dim, but that it may ſerve to guide this preſent age into the paths of virtue, &amp; reſolutions of loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty: nay, it may ſerve as a help to detect and diſcover the falſhood, treachery, cowardiſe, and ignoble diſloyalty of many, whom neither the laws of God, nor of the Land, have been ſtrong enough to oblige them to the duty and Allegiance they owe and ought ever to pay to their Soveraign. But theſe, and all other morall examples of this kind,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:58102:34"/>come infinitely ſhort of that tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendent worth, that appeared ſo glorious in this noble <hi>Iſraelite;</hi> for their grounds were at beſt, but Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, Emulation or Intereſt, and though founded on the baſis of virtue, friendſhip, or fortitude, yet their chiefeſt Actions and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours were accompnied with vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glory and arrogancy, if not tainte and ſtained with revenge, proud am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, or ſordid avarice. But <hi>Huſhai</hi> was led to his duty by the light of grace, by the gratitude of a noble mind, by the laws of God which commandeth<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal</hi> 105.</note> 
               <hi>Touchnott mine Anointed,</hi> becauſe as the wiſeman<note n="e" place="margin">Wiſ. <hi>6.3.</hi> Data eſt à Domino po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtas regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, &amp; vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus ab al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisſimo.</note> aſſureth <hi>power is given to Kings from the Lord, and Soveraignty from the Highest.</hi> St. <hi>Paul,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore writing to the Roman Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, directs in the Apoſtolical Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non<note n="f" place="margin">Rom. <hi>13.1.</hi> Rom. <hi>13.4.</hi> Non tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ſummo magistratui ſed infimis quibuſvis magiſtratus poteſtate fuugenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>betur obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dientia. Theod. Beza. Annota.</note> 
               <hi>Let every Soul be ſubject to the higher powers.</hi> And this is backt with many reaſons, becauſe Kings
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:58102:34"/>receive their ſword from God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are his miniſters, becauſe they are impowered to protect and puniſh, and from this principle and fountain of evangelical truth, it Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally flows and follows, that Kings in their perſons, and in their lawful heirs and ſucceſſours, and in all their juſt rights and commands are to be obſerved and obeyed. Hence it is, that Iews and Chriſtians, Greeks and Barbarians, all perſons of all ſorts, are commanded, to render to every man what is due, whether it be Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute, fear or honour; and that duty is to be performed <hi>not only for wrath, but for conſcience ſake.</hi>
               <note place="margin">non prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter iram ſed propter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientiam. Rom. <hi>13.</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>Rom. <hi>13.2.</hi>
               </note> The rule ſeemes poſitive and infallible: that <hi>whoſoever reſiſteth the power, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth the ordinance of God, and they that reſiſt ſhall receive to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves damnation:</hi> St. <hi>Peter</hi> was as highly concern'd in this point with the Iews, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> with the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, and therefore they are directed
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:58102:35"/>and taught to <hi>ſubmit themſelves to every Ordinance of man for the Lords ſake,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13. <hi>p.</hi> 17.</note> 
               <hi>whether it be to King as ſupream, or unto Governours, as unto them that are ſent by him:</hi> this command is redoubled again by the ſame Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>Fear God, honour the King.</hi> So then the duty of loyalty and allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to Princes is not only ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on legal but evangelical princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and hath not only Prophetical but Apoſtolical foundations to war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and ſupport this truth: and as the primitive and beſt Chriſtians, both in their active and paſſive obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, gave teſtimony of this truth even to Heathen and Pagan Princes, and Emperours; ſo Chriſt, who is the way, the truth and the life, preached this doctrine and commanded to give unto <hi>Caeſar,</hi> what was <hi>Caeſars,</hi> &amp; to God what was Gods. This day ſpring from an high probably did influence and enlighten <hi>Huſhai</hi> the <hi>Archites</hi> noble and loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:58102:35"/>Soul, who ſeaſonably and ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully encountred the greateſt danger, diſappointed the deepeſt policy, and diſſolved and diſperſed the moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural Treaſon that the age had hatched or produced, wherein King <hi>David</hi> lived; and it is a just obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that lyeth ſtrictly on the reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and affections of all ſubjects to the utmoſt of their reaſon and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, to imitate, if not exceed the great worth and virtue of this no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Archite</hi> in their duty and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voirs towards their Soveraign, who being a Chriſtian Monarch of a lawful Royal line, for the ſucceſſion of many hundred years, may expect and require moſt juſtly the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act performance of loyalty and true Allegiance: and that not only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe preſcription, cuſtom, reaſon, &amp; laws, but ſacred oaths, which are the higheſt bonds; and call God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to witneſſe, oblige and conjure the ſubjects to their fidelity and duty;
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:58102:36"/>and this was performed punctually and compleatly by <hi>Huſhai</hi> to King <hi>David,</hi> who being one of the ſons of <hi>Ieſse,</hi> was the firſt of his family who ſate on the throne, and ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with as much conflict as honour, his unhappy predeceſſor <hi>Saul:</hi> yet this noble perſon, though the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy was but a later foundation, &amp; tranſlated from the houſe of <hi>Saul</hi> to the houſe of <hi>David;</hi> yet he did neither boggle nor ſtartle, &amp; though <hi>Abſalon</hi> by his flattery of reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion inſnared and infatuated the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular multitudes, pretending juſtice when he traiterouſly invaded the perſon of the King, and the prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatives of the Crown, yet none of theſe circumſtances, nor, that the head-piece and politician <hi>Achito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phel,</hi> was in the conſpiracy, could de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Huſhai</hi> from his duty, but that he would adventure his life, fortune and all that was dear to him in the Kings cauſe, and ſo juſt a neceſſity:
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:58102:36"/>he reſolved that his courage, his wiſdome and his fidelity could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be more ſerviceable, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this loyal ſubject is more active and diligent to preſerve King <hi>Davids</hi> rights, and to immortallize his own honour, in this unfortunate juncture of extremities: many thouſands loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al ſubjects of his Majeſties three Kingdomes, had <hi>Huſhaies</hi> reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and affections in the late barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and unnatural wars; ſome roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aliſts by virtue of their Soveraignes commiſſion raiſed troops of Horſe and foot, fortyfied Townes and Caſtles, equipped ſhips, and uſing the utmoſt of their endeavours, hazarded their lives, relations and fortunes, and to render a full aſſurance of their loyalty to their Prince were not daunted with fire or ſword, nor diſcouraged with impriſonment, baniſhment, or any degree of the moſt tormenting cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cruelties, nay death, in ſo juſt a cauſe
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:58102:37"/>leading and laying them in a bed of honour; they feared neither the loſſe of limbs or lives in their ſervice of their King and Country: and when (after many tedious years) their forces, ſubdued by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive power, or betrayed by cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Treachery, did fail, the Kings party cheriſhed loyalty in their hearts, and though they were plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred unmercifully, ſequeſtred and decimated illegally, and forced to ſlaviſh compoſitions, and haraſed with cruel aſperities and ignominies, as bitter as death; yet aſſoon as their Hair, as <hi>Sampſons,</hi> did begin to ſpring, after ſo many ſharp raiſors and ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings, and their ſtrength began to come to them, they were active in their deſigns and in their contrivan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ever attempting ſome noble en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſe, that might recover their King to his Throne, and themſelves to the liberty and priviledge of free born ſubjects, ſome in their capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:58102:37"/>attended his Majeſtie, and the royal branches in their perigrination abroad: others as laborious Bees toiled and worked (if the day was fair and ſecure) in their ſeveral ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions or circuits of their intereſts, in their own Countryes. And (up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on occaſion) ſaluting or taſting the inclination of every flour they met with, they make it their only buſineſs to convey the thyme and hony of true loyalty to the Royal Hive: ſome are very active in their purſes, others turned the cock to the ſtreams of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens plenty, others in their prayers: ſome did uſe their moſt refi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned abilities, to diſtract the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of the many headed monſter the long (at laſt,) Rumping Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament: ſome noble ſpirits (who dearly paid for their Teſtimony of Loyalty) deſigned the death of the grand Impoſture and Uſurper, <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel,</hi> whoſe Son like an <hi>Ignis Fatuus</hi> quickly vaniſhed: ſome gave with
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:58102:38"/>daring ingenuity, and occaſion of great diſtraction in the Army, and rais'd jealouſies, and diſtruſt amongſt the Officers and ſoldiers: ſome, for many years diſcreetly acted their parts and very proſperouſly, amongſt the Aldermen, Common Councel, and more Eminent ſtickling Citizens, who being eaſily perſwaded, that Trade generally decayed, that their ſhips were taken dayly by the men of war at ſea, and that a pinching Poverty was ready to ſeaze on them, armed themſelves privately, and as ſome of the gallant Senators ſtoutly (on ſeveral occaſions) told the Relicks of the long Parliament, the Committy of Safety, and Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of the Army, that The Treaſure of the City was exhauſted, trade ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly loſt, and many thouſand fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies impoveriſhed.</p>
            <p>So neither could nor would they advance any monies any further, to maintain that diſorderly and illegal
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:58102:38"/>rabble of <hi>Ianizaries</hi> and Soldiers, who as they had a long time inter, rupted the proſperity and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce in the Citty, and over the whole land. So they now reſolved to defend their Liberties, Rights and Properties, as carefully as their lives, and being threatned with terrour and menaces of Plundering, impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment, and other hoſtile and hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid injuries by fire and ſword, they very gallantly replyed, that they would unanimouſly ſtand on their guards, to defend themſelves, maugre all oppoſition, as they had proſperouſly in ſuch caſes of dang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, when they ſuſpected a tumultua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry riſing of the rabble in the reigns of King <hi>Richard</hi> the third, when he marched againſt <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeventh to the battaile at <hi>Boſworth-field:</hi> as they had in King <hi>Henry</hi> the eights reign when he went to <hi>Bullen</hi> in <hi>France:</hi> as they had equipaged them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> reign <hi>An.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:58102:39"/>Dom.</hi> 1588. And according to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral preſidents of this kind; for which ſervices the City received ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn thanks from the Crown, for their great care of themſelves and the Royal City, as it appears in their City records and tranſactions of their political affaires: they then thus provoked, thus diſpoſed, quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſolved to hold faſt their purſes, though they could neither their tongues nor their hands; monyes (the nerves of the monſtruous body, ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly ſhrinking,) the Officers of the Army fell into diſtraction, and the private ſouldiers wanting pay, quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly began to raile and revile, to kick and to cut, and to ſcorne &amp; caſhiere their Officers, &amp; in a few dayes both became as odious as ridiculous, to the generality of the people of the three Kingdomes, who reſolving to ſhake of their Iron yoke of vaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage, comforted themſelves in their hopefull poſſibilities. And as lines
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:58102:39"/>running moſt naturally to the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, began to fix their thoughts and hopes in their Soveraignes Reſtau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. The hearts of men waxing warm with theſe deſires, and poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities, they began to talk freely and plainly that neither City nor Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try could be happy until the King ſhould be reſtored, that the whole Land was in a ſad confuſion and horrid diſtreſs; and the City and Common Councel diſcerning a happy conjunction of affection and aſſiſtance from all parts, ſent ſtout anſwers (on ſeveral occaſions) to the tedious long Parliament, to the Officers of the Army, to <hi>Fleet wood,</hi> and his <hi>Walling for dians</hi> at the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of ſafety; that the City was for want of Trade and through the loſſe of many hundred ſhips ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poveriſhed, and reduced to ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremities, that they neither could nor would advance any further ſummers of monyes. Theſe unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecte
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:58102:40"/>Reſolutions and aſſurances, cauſed the Enemies of Monarchy</p>
            <p>Firſt, to ſhiver and ſplinter into diſtraction, and then to fall into deſpaire, and each Brother growing jealous of his Fellow Traitor, guilt of horrid Crimes: in ſecuring their condition, the better to avoide po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular fury, they think of addreſſes to the clemency of their Prince, which in ſuch high offences, is ever the happieſt refuge and <hi>Aſylum,</hi> whiles the ſimptomes of the new modeld Anarchy thus fully appeare. And the frame of the monſtrous and tottering Government was thus ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken: many noble <hi>Huſhaies,</hi> and true Royalliſts, <note place="margin">The Duke of <hi>Albe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marle,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Bath,</hi>
               </note> took faſt hold on theſe encouraging opportunities, and moſt ſucceſsfully, proved moſt wiſe conducters of Affairs, mightily tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Reſtauration of the King, and with his Majeſty;<note place="margin">The Lord Biſhop of <hi>Hereford.</hi>
               </note> the recovery of our Religion, liberties and laws, which without his preſence and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:58102:40"/>protection ſeemed much like to a conſumptive dying patient, ready at the laſt gaſp to give up the Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>But whiles theſe unſpotted Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alliſts for almoſt twenty years conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance in a confuſed Government, and the outrages of a Civil war, were conſtantly Active or Paſſive in their duty for the Crown. Another party (either conſcious of their er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, or convinced in their judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or at leaſt concerned in their reſpective intereſt,) ſhewed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves like brothers of the half bloud, to have a deep reſentment of the great injuries, perpetrated againſt an imperial Crown, and to own their fellow ſubjects for Auxiliaries and Coadjutors in the publick concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their King and Country, which like a violent torrent, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verflowing inundation, carrying all before it, circled the Presbyterians in the ſame intereſt: and as Iews, Turks, Pagans, and Chriſtians, in
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:58102:41"/>a ſtorm or tempeſt at Sea, exerciſe their wits, pour our their prayers, imploy their hands to ſave the ſhip, that after the ſtorm, all Paſſengers may arrive ſafe on ſhoar: (for ſo did <hi>Ionah</hi> with the <hi>Mariners,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ionah</hi> 1.2. <hi>Act.</hi> 27.17.</note> and St. <hi>Paul</hi> with the <hi>Souldiers.</hi>) So all par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the three Kingdomes, ſeeing the Royal Soveraign ſailing with ſo proſperous a Gale, and that the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of Heaven had ſo ordered, that the King inevitably ſhould be reſtored, they put on the loyal dreſs, and if not to ſerve their King, yet to preſerve themſelves, appear on the ſuddain courtly converts and perfect royaliſts, and as every good ſubject is obliged to rejoice at the Kings reſtauration to the Crown, ſo is he to congratulate the converſion of his Enemies to thoſe principles which cannot but confirm and juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie his reſolutions to loyalty for ever.</p>
            <p>But this latter or ſecond ſort of
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:58102:41"/>converted ſubjects come ſomwhat ſhort of the excellency and worth of thoſe nobler minds, which were never ſtayned with Apoſtacy or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection from the crown, and they are more deeply obliged to duty and fidelity, to loyalty and gratitude to their Prince, becauſe they are not only ſecured by his clemencie and pardon, but likewiſe have liberally taſted of his bounty and favours, and though the royal party, like the poor <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in <hi>AEgypt</hi> endured much bondage, and yoaks, hard task<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſters, trod clay, and made brick; and in the ſavage wilderneſſe of horrid confuſion, were pinched with cold and nakedneſſe, and had there ſouls filled with ſcorn and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach: yet they are not envious at their reconciled Brethrens happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, nor troubled that they have portions and dividents in the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> and ſhare with them in the bleſſings of his Majeſties reſtau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:58102:42"/>ſubmiſſively recommending all ſuch comfortable poſſibilities to the providence of God, and to the goodneſs, bounty, wiſdome and juſtice of their Prince; who can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but out of ſo many ſad afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons gain much knowledge, and by ſuch an univerſal experience of the humours and tempers of his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, diſcern more clearly, whom to employ or truſt, and whom to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote, paſſe by, or puniſh: all this while, theres no pretence for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe, much leſs of merit, in recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled and converted Enemies. Firſt, for excuſe or apologies, the moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent can hardly plead any thing above a ſimplicity of their hearts, as thoſe ſilly ſheep who hearkned too much to <hi>Abſolons</hi> flattery: and though liberty of conſcience, a through Reformation of Religion, and the laws, the hopes of more clear Goſpel truths, and a more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act and perfect way to Heaven, and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:58102:42"/>many ſuch canting, cunning, and jugling pretences, were, as more pleaſant baits whiſpered in the ear, ſwelled from the Preſs, and thundred cheatingly from the Pulpits: yet the the late Royal Martyr in his prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical ſpirit and golden pen, found out the malice, treaſon, fraud &amp; maligni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of thoſe intoxicating and vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous deluſions, adviſing his dear Son the Prince, with his own obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,<note n="g" place="margin">Kings book Εικον Βασιλικε pag. 235.</note> that the Devil of Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on doth commonly turn himſelf in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an Angel of Reformation, &amp; the old Serpent can pretend new lights: when ſome mens conſciences ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe them for ſedition and faction, they ſtop its mouth with the name and noiſe of Religion, when Piety pleads for Peace and Patience, they cry out zeal; ſo the worſt of men, lurk under the pretenſions of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of Religion, and auſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious beginnings have often the worſt deſigns. In the judgement
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:58102:43"/>and Counſel then of this ſacred O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator, there can be no excuſe for traiterous errors and ſuch diſloyal deviations. King <hi>Iames</hi> of ever bleſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed memory, gave the like advice to Prince <hi>Henry</hi> his Son, commanding him as a Father and a King. Take heed therefore my Son to ſuch Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritans, very peſts in the Church and Common-weale, whom no deſerts can oblige, neither oathes nor pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes binde, breathing nothing but ſedition and calumnies, aſpiring without meaſure,<note place="margin">K. <hi>Iames</hi> in the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of a King p. 9.</note> railing without reaſon, and making their own ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations (without any warrant of the word) the ſquare of their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences: from theſe words the King raiſeth his reſentment of injured Majeſtie, ſaying. I proteſt before the great God, and ſince I am here upon my teſtament, it is no place for me to ly in, that ye ſhall never find with any highland or border Thieves, greater ingratitude, and more lyes
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:58102:43"/>and vile perjuries then with theſe Phanatick ſpirits; and ſuffer not the principles of them to brook your land, if you like to ſit at reſt. Theſe two royal Princes had much judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and wiſdome, great learning and experience. The one tels the world that theſe virulent Phana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks did perſecute him before he was born, being not at reſt in his Royal mothers womb, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther having ſuffered many injuries in his life, was ſooner hurryed to an ignoble and untimely death. As to excuſes and apologies, it was the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient ſatanical deviſe, which having firſt ruined <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded them to extenuate their infideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, diſobedience and crime, with a ſecond kind of errour, pleading e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven before God himſelf, as <hi>Adam,</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen. 3.12.13.</hi> Vnde tibi hoc accidit? quis te in tantam in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duxit alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rationem <hi>St. Chryſ.</hi> in Geneſ.</note> It was not <hi>I</hi> but the <hi>Woman,</hi> and ſo <hi>Eve,</hi> it was not <hi>I</hi> but the <hi>Serpent;</hi> but an ingenuous confeſſion is the beſt and ſureſt remedy in the caſe of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquency,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:58102:44"/>and Repentance proves the beſt cordial in ſuch a fowl and loathſome dangerous diſeaſe: it is not then a way to impunity or par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don to plead, I was miſguided or miſtaken, tranſported with zeal, or catched by the ears by the inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of deluding Hypocrites: theſe and ſuch thin fig-leaves, are not competent or comly veiles to cover or excuſe ſins of ſuch a ſcarlet com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion, nor jealouſies and fears, which have blown up ſome, into tumultuous and rebellious reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, an ingenious acknowledgment of crimes and errous committed, with the promiſe and practiſe of loyalty and true obedience, is a more exact and ready path to ſafety and ſatisfaction: and as for apologies and excuſes, none may (in the leaſt degree pretend to them,) who have been ſuch laviſh prodigals of the King and Kingdomes bloud and Treaſure, and as there is no place
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:58102:44"/>for apologies or excuſes, ſo much leſs for merit or deſerts, for though many did grow weary of uſurpation, Tyranny and injuries towards their King and the loyal party, or rather (diſappointed of thoſe ends of pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and command, which they phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cied and propoſed to themſelves,) began to totter, and turn from thoſe poſſibilities to which they had leaned ſo long, yet by aſſed by a different faction and Intereſt, they reflect on the Crown, with a loyal aſpect, and in this ſecond choice engage their perſons and party, and run many dangers and hazards of life and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune to make themſelves conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and this ſervice or alteration, (though from a diſcontented party, or reconciled enemy) in policy, was not to be refuſed or unacceptable, for though it might not much ſtrengthen the King, yet in ſome proportion, it did debilitate and weaken the enemy, and it might be
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:58102:45"/>probably hoped, that as ſome bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches had fallen from the Rebellious body; others might follow their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, or at leaſt learn from them, that an Army or party, like a houſe or Kingdome divided within it ſelf, hath no long duration and cannot ſtand, this declenſion from evil prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, as it was an external teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of repentance and grace, ſo it muſt be acknowledged to be good ſervice, and a fair <hi>praeludium</hi> to future good effects: but duty and endeavour of this Nature may rather and more fitly be reputed expiations for for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer crimes, then pretenſions to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and merit, which ever (as the acute School men teſtify)<note n="i" place="margin">Moritum importat aqualitatem juſtitiae Aquin. <hi>3.</hi> quas. <hi>19.</hi>
               </note> imply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and importeth an equality of juſtice and right: and juſtice doth not beg but boldly plead for deſert and merit, and to have and receive its rights, not out of bounty or fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, but as its due and debt: a ſove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Throne cannot endure ſuch
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:58102:45"/>petulant and bold pleaders. This temper were rather tolerable in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quals, (and Kings know none) then inferiours, and might better ſute with commanders, (and ſoveraign Kings acknowledge none but God,<note place="margin">Rex a Deo primus nulli ſecundus.</note>) then with thoſe who have been offenders: and in the higheſt privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges ought to attend as humble petitioners. So then, though the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice be never ſo infinite, yet riſing from the art and power of thoſe who have ſo deeply offended: there can be no pretences to merit, which in a ſecond reveiw, is not to be granted, or admitted without a leſſoning &amp; diminution to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatives of ſoveraignty which is ſo abſolute, that it cannot endure any intimation of command.<note n="k" place="margin">Meritum est actio qua juſtum eſt ut agen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti aliquid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>detur. Aquin. <hi>3.49. c. 6.</hi>
               </note> Now merit (as the Schools teach) is an action whereby, it is not only might but neceſſary, that reward and recompence be payed as a debt, to
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:58102:46"/>him who hath acted: now when the Actions and prevarications of thoſe who have ſo highy injured, and deeply wounded ſoveraignty, and diſturbed the peace and proſperity of three Kingdomes, are ballanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and put into the Scales with their good works of loyalty, (though never ſo weighty) they will be found utterly too light for reward or merit, and rather juſtly prove ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of their Princes grace and cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency: and in caſe their ſoveraign, like <hi>Ahaſuerus,</hi> have inclined his royal Scepter towards them, and thereby teſtified his bounty and goodneſſe, and ſo capacitated them with royal favour, truſt and honour, theſe obligations as they magnifie the virtue of the Prince, ſo they are as ſo many ſtronger chains, to bind thoſe who are obliged by them, to greater perfection of loyalty, and more exact and vigilant perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances of their duty, or elſe thoſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:58102:46"/>will prove as ſo many witneſſes to evidence againſt them, and to accuſe them of odious and monſtruous ingratitude.<note place="margin">Meritum congrui &amp;, condigni Aquin. <hi>l. 2. q. I 14. c. 6.</hi>
               </note> And as to the <hi>medium</hi> or modification of the School diſtinction of condignity or is not to be admitted in this caſe for that of condignity or adequate me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is abſolutely taken away, and that of congruity, or rather conveniency is totally and intirely to be recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to the Princes Will, Grace, Wiſdome and Iudgement, who as he pleaſeth, may promote or puniſh as well as pardon, by act of indemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or amneſty, as to royal pleaſure, ſhall ſeem expedient. Apologies and excuſes in delinquents thus explo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and all pretences to merit in thoſe who have legally forfeited their lives, liberties and eſtates, by the laws of the land, utterly abroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, what refuge can ſuch offenders fly and addreſs to, as cordials to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve their honour, or their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:58102:47"/>perhaps ſome may plead, their promiſe, their vow, their proteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their engagement, or the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, or their abjuration: theſe were, (if righty judged &amp; exammined,) cunning, ſubtile, and ſinful deſigns in the projectors and contrivers, who framed them, were Trumpets of Rebellion: Sedition and faction: ſounded and blown up by thoſe who promoted them, and proved as ſnares to their Souls, who either weakly ſubmitted, or with tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizing appetites did greedily ſwallow them, and theſe cobweb lines (ſpun out of the body &amp; womb of a veni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous ſpider,) are not ſtrong enough to hold a ſubjects hand or heart from his duty of faith &amp; allegiance to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his Soveraign; and each one of theſe feeble and ſubſequent obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions being ſifted by truth and reaſon, as well as laws and juſtice will crumble to nothing, before the oathes of allegiance and ſupremacy,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:58102:47"/>and the light of that duty, that by municipal decrees, by the laws of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, &amp; birth-right, every ſubject ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to his Prince, being born under his prerogative and power, &amp; in any of his Kingdomes or Dominions.</p>
            <p>Firſt as to promiſes<note n="l" place="margin">Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsio eſt actus iatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, quia eſt enuntiatio &amp; ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio alicujus. T. Aquin. <hi>22.</hi> quae. <hi>88. a. 1.</hi>
               </note> (which are the ſuddain, and uſually moſt tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſient verbal obligations, and ought to be effected of all perſons of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, Religion and Honour) they ought ever to be acts of ſound reaſon and judgement, raiſed on good foundations, and duly conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, before they come to be pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed and proclaimed by the tongue or ſigned by the hand, and even the ſtricteſt promiſes or paroles, do not oblige the Faith or Honour of him that<note n="m" place="margin">Promiſsa non debent ſecurari, ſi eſtillicitum quod pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittiur: vel ſi ſint muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae conditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis perſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, vel negotiorum. Ad hoc er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go quod ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo debeat ſervare quod pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſerat oportet ut ſit licitum quod pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittitur, &amp; quod omnia immutata permaneant Aquin. <hi>22</hi> ae. queſt. <hi>110. a. 35.</hi>
               </note> promiſeth, if what be promiſed be <hi>illicit,</hi> or unlawful, or if the conditions of Perſons or affairs be changed and altered. Theſe eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentials rightly conſidered, what e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver promiſes have been made by
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:58102:48"/>ſubjects againſt the ſoveraignty of their Princes liberties, of their Country &amp; laws of the land, do fall to the Ground, &amp; diſſolve of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, becauſe of their <hi>illicit</hi> &amp; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unlawful foundation, And as to the mutation of perſons or affaires, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects are not to make new promiſes of combination or conſpiracy, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the true old principles of faith, and true allegiance to their Kings, for whether they ſit gloriouſly and puiſſantly on their thrones, or by any black misfortune, are reduced to a low degree, their character is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delible, and being Gods vice-gerent: in all conditions, their ſubjects owe them reverence and true allegiance. The firſt ſcruple thus eaſily blown over, the ſecond may prove of leſſer difficulty: ſome more zealous then judicious, proceed further, and plead they have not only promiſed, but vowed; now a vow ſeems to be a cord of ſtronger twiſting, the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:58102:48"/>becauſe an act of more ſerious conſultation, and of more ſacred reſtriction:<note n="n" place="margin">Votum à voluntate dictum quaſi delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratione &amp; propoſitio profectum Buca in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit Theo. <hi>l. 45.</hi>
               </note> promiſes, are common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly made to men, but<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: ſic Euſtath.</note> Vowes ſeem to mount a ſtep higher, and being offered to the Deity, are obſerved with a more divine and dreadfull atteſtation of God; and to violate vowes is much more dangerous, the votaries may plead, but in this point it will appear, that an unlawful vow is as eaſily and juſtly to be broken, as a raſh and undiſcreet or diſloyal promiſe, the rather becauſe a vow properly is an<note n="p" place="margin">Votum eſt actus latriae &amp; Religionis Tho. Aqui. <hi>22 ae q 88. a 5.</hi> Votum pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsio Deo facta de meliori bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no. idem, Votum teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficatio quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsionis ſpontanea qua debet fieri Deo, de iis quae Dei ſunt. Aqui. <hi>22</hi>ae. queſt. <hi>88.</hi> Ad Votum tria requirunt, deliberatio, Propoſitum, &amp; promiſsio. idem.</note> act of religious worſhip. It is a promiſe to God of the intention &amp; reſolution to ſome bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter good, becauſe it is a ſolemn teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of a deliberated voluntary promiſe made and offered unto God, to perfect and compleat which, are
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:58102:49"/>a reſolute purpoſe and a certain or conſtant promiſe. Now theſe cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances and requiſites are ſuch, as the votary need nor err, unleſs he will be affectely ignorant, or raſhly and willfully ſinful. Now for a ſubject to vow to that which is unlawful, to ſigne to that which is ſinful, to offer ſuch a ſacrifice to God, which is odious and unaccep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, is an aggravation of the crime: and therefore not to be kept, but to be broken off, with more bitter re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penrance and more zealous deteſta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion<note n="q" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Votum te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merarium &amp; illegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timum; quod de re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus illcitis; malo fine ae perſonis etiam non ui juris ſuscipitur Bucan. The. Inſtit. <hi>I. 45.</hi> queſt. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> And if every perty ſin be offenſive before the eternal God, how abominable muſt thoſe ſins appear, which like ſcarlet and crim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon are of a double dye, aggravated with ſollemn vows and promiſſes, and yet ſo much the more ſinful be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe attempted and perpetrated, by thoſe, who in the caſe of loyalty, as ſubjects, cannot be abſolved from their oaths of allegiance to their
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:58102:49"/>King: and ſo not being <hi>ſui juris,</hi> at liberty, have no power to make <hi>illicit,</hi> vows of this kind, and are not to give ſo much as conſent to their illegallity. The ſubjects in This caſe of allegiance being as ſtrictly reſtrained, and durifully ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to their Prince in his power and pleaſure, and the juſtneſſe of the laws, as children under the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of their Parents, as a Wife du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the life of her Husband, as ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants are obliged to their Maſters until they are at liberty<note n="r" place="margin">Num <hi>30.4.5.7.</hi> Votum ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae vincu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum. Vota eorum infringi poterant.</note>: If a vow (though lawful) were by Gods word thus ſtated in the power of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, the Husband, the Maſter, <hi>a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nore ad majus:</hi> much more are <hi>illicit</hi> vows to be abrogated and broken, in ſubjects vowing, not only againſt their Princes conſent, but againſt the houour and ſafety of their ſacred perſons, and their royal Crown and dignity, by theſe arguments, it plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appears that neither raſh and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:58102:50"/>adviſed promiſes, nor ſerious ſinful, and deliberated vows are to be kept or obſerved no more then that <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nathema,</hi> under which ſome deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate zealous bloudy Iews bound themſelves neither to eat, nor drink, till they had ſlain St. <hi>Paul.</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act. 23.12.14.</hi> Stulto zelo correpti mentiri &amp; occidere quidvis denique tibi licere arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trabantur <hi>T.</hi> Beza in loc.</note>
            </p>
            <p>There is a third bond or obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that ſome tender curioſities lay hold on,<note place="margin">The 3. proteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> and that is the proteſtation, which (though never formed nor forced into the nature of a munici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal and binding law) yet was cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly deviſed by ſome ſtate politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians, and ſent and diſperſed over the Kingdomes, to taſte the inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the people, or at leaſt as <hi>Shiboleth,</hi> to diſtinguiſh who were really and truly Royaliſts, and who were not, which form of obliging a party (very probably) took its ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample from <hi>Germany,</hi> where the <hi>Lutherans</hi> ſolemnly proteſted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſome doctrinal and practical, proceeding of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:58102:50"/>And from this root ſprang the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraction that thoſe reformed Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, who deſerted the communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Roman Church, were commonly called Proteſtants: but the proteſtation of a later and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liamentary conception and birth, was not ſo much to diſtinguiſh Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians of ſeveral Churches, as to diſcern perſons how they ſtood affected to the King, or to his great Councel, whether they would as loyal ſubjects adhere to the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty of their Prince, or (in caſe his Majeſty diſſented from his two houſes) whether they would ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture all, and to live and dye with a Parliamentary party of their fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low ſubjects, and be ſubſervient to their ends and intereſts, this proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was an early cunning bait, and like <hi>Manna</hi> it pleaſed moſt pallats, becauſe it contained in it a variety of lawful good things, and what could be more acceptable to a true
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:58102:51"/>Son of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> then to defend her doctrine? what duty more agreeable to a ſubject then to defend the prerogatives of his Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigns crown, and what endeavour more honourable then to preſerve the priviledges of Parliament, and the laws of the land? Theſe four diſhes ſeaſonably ſerved might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh well, and find a good digeſtion being duties in themſelves, rightly underſtood, fit for a good reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in any ſubject, who honoured his King, loved his Country, or had a care of his ſoul, yet the branches of that proteſtation, did ſpread into ſo great a latitude, in reſpect of the variety of the definitive points of the doctrine of the Church, the unli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted prerogatives of the Crown, undetermined priviledges of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and the difficulty of underſtanding the multitude, and body of the learned laws, that after the proteſtation was licked in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:58102:51"/>a form, &amp; as a golden pill quickly ſwallowed by about t weny mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Commons Houſe. The pill being taſted by a more judicious pallate, was disreliſhed, and had ſtopt there, if theſe words, <hi>viz.</hi> (as far as lawfully I may) had not as a more ſafe ingredient been added to it, &amp; there (as if a warrantable diſpenſation had been given to every mans conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, ſenſe and reaſon,) it was clearly ſwallowed without chawing, or the leaſt diſpute.</p>
            <p>The proteſtation, then was (at moſt) but a conditional aſſeverati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſtuffed with great variety of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties and obſcurityes. And though the doctrine of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> the Kings prerogative and the laws of the land had elbow-room in thoſe few lines, yet the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges of that Parliament, which in time, deſtroyed the King, the Church and the laws, (under a ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous name,) deluded the bewitched people into a horrid rebellion which
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:58102:52"/>cauſed great miſery &amp; devaſtation to three flouriſhing Kingdomes, &amp; now when thoſe, who took the proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, have conſidered of the contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances, intrigues, &amp; intereſts of that cunning trap and popular bait, they ought to retreat from the danger of thoſe ſnares: &amp; now having recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red their ſenſe and reaſon by repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance and a better conſultation, may better know how to perform their duty to God in his Church, and to their King and Country.</p>
            <p>The mask of the proteſtation thus pul'd off, and the curtaines drawn, the face of loyalty is more clear and viſible: yet there is another brood, and ſort of perſons, who cry out of their peirced and wounded conſciences, and tell the world they have with hearts and hands lifted up to heaven, taken the national and general covenant, and they cannot quit fairly with this delight and darling of their ſoules. This, as <hi>Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:58102:52"/>from <hi>Iupiter</hi> (they urge) fell from Heaven, and though the Covenant was the contrivance of a few con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federated ſeditious heads, yet the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venanters hold themſelves obliged to keep it as ſtirctly, as if it had been the breath, motion and dictates of the ſacred ſpirit of God, and many ſuppoſe that having lifted up their hands in a pious deluſion, they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not nor muſt not let them fall in a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentant and humble ſubmiſſion to their Soveraign, and the laws of their Country: but ſuch infatuated Zelots are much deceived, and ought to ſee more clearly, the ſcales of their deluſion being taken from their eyes, but if an irrational ſturdy obſtinacy ſtill poſſeſs their reſolutions, willfulneſſe, blind's rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and obduration cauterize their conſciences: their beſt cure may be procured by adviſing with the incomparable reaſons of the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſity of <hi>Oxford</hi> againſt the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant:
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:58102:53"/>&amp; if thoſe reaſons, prove not a welcome ſoveraign cordial, let ſuch paſſionate Zelots apply them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to their Princes remedy, and <hi>Probatum,</hi> or for ever hold them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in their Honour, Souls and Conſciences to be incurable. And the late bleſſed Royal Martyr, <hi rend="sup">t</hi> doth moſt pathetically and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfully adviſe and argue.<note place="margin">Εικον Βασιλικε chap. 14. of the covenant pag. 110.</note> The en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joynings of Oathes upon people muſt needs, in things doubtfull, be dangerous, as in things unlawfull, damnnable, &amp; no leſſe ſuperfluous, where former religious &amp; legall En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements, bound men ſufficiently to all neceſſary duties: nor can I ſee how they will reconcile ſuch an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novating Oath and Covenant, with that former proteſtation, which was ſo lately taken to maintain the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion eſtabliſhed in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> ſince they count diſcipline ſo great a part of Religion. And in the the next page the King ſaith (in
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:58102:53"/>the candor and kindneſs of his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit) I am prone to believe and hope that many who take the covenant, are yet firm to this judgement, that ſuch later vows, oathes or leagues can never blot out thoſe former gravings and characters, which by juſt and lawful Oathes were made upon their Souls. And again, the bleſſed King urgeth the third time, that which makes ſuch confederati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons by way of Solemn Leagues and covenants, more to be ſuſpected, is, that they are the common road in all factions and powerful perturbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of State or Church, where for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malities of extraordinary zeal and piety, are ever more ſtudied and elaborate, then, when Politicians moſt agitate deſperate deſigns, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all that is ſetled or Sacred in Religion and Laws; which by ſuch ſervice, are cunningly yet forcibly wreſted by ſecret ſteps, and leſs ſenſible degrees, from their known
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:58102:54"/>rule and wonted practiſe to comply with the humour of thoſe men, who aime to ſubdue all to their own will and power, under the diſguiſes of holy combinations. Theſe were the counſels and command of a dying King, who ſealed theſe truths with his royal bloud, and they may ſerve as cautions or preventive phyſick, not to be refuſed; as cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dials, to comfort languiſhing and fainting ſpirits, as ſoveraign reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes, to recover relapſed patients, to a ſound and heathful diſpoſition of both Soul and body, and they are not to be neglected or deſpiſed by any rational ſubjects, but who doom themſelves to diſcontent, or will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully are dementated to a ſelf perdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>When the proteſtation and the covenant,<note place="margin">3. Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> like old and uſeleſs Alma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacks were laid aſide, a ſucceſſive jugling, prevailing party found out vicious matter, to compoſe new
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:58102:54"/>bird lime, and ſhuffling the cards, and then cutting and dealing cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly, deviſed by an <hi>Engagement</hi> to catch ſome credulous and timorous complying inclinations, or at leaſt, utterly to pack the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> out of the ſtock of power and intereſt. This obortive <hi>Embrìo</hi> and <hi>Precoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> birth was quickly tumbled out of the body of the bear, and by ſome ſmooth bloudy tongues licked into a form, or rather confuſion of words; which reduced to neither mood or figure, were ſo illogical, that the <hi>Engagement</hi> was looked on as a factious ſeditious ſnare, and not ſtrong enough to hold the foot of the lighteſt <hi>Larke.</hi> The weakeſt perſon that complyed to be entang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in it, as to the form (if any) it was a ſubſcribed promiſe, before an illegal Magiſtrate. And as to the matter, it was a fancy or dream like that of <hi>Vtopia,</hi> of a common wealth which was no where in <hi>England,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:58102:55"/>in ſome mens brains, who were ſick of ambition, and pride, and long'd for Government. This repub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick they ſtiled, ſetled, when the world ſaw the-three Kingdomes in diſorder and confuſion, and the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours and Abettors of this Ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous monſter, panting, quaking, and ſculking under continual ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and the pinching torments of fears and jealouſies: but that which occaſioned greateſt ſcorn and laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of this ſeditious bug-bear, was, that it was covetouſly contrived, to be a vendible commodity, and ſo eaſily gain'd from the juſtice of Peace or his Clark, for half a Crown; and in a ſhort time it prov'd a more common contemptible drug, and was familiarly bought for twelve pence, until at laſt, it was not valu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. On which deviſe, all judicious and ſober Perſons did look as a ſtate cheat, or a meer moral promiſe to things imaginary, irrational and
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:58102:55"/>impoſſible under the preſſure of tyrannical uſurpers, and in it ſelf no way legal or binding, being like tow in an inſtant ſet on fire by ſome ſulphurous ſparks, and flaming for a moment, dyed and was ſuddenly extinguiſhed.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Vſus juran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di ducit ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minem ad perjurium. D Ber. ſer. <hi>32.</hi> de per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurio.</note>A fourth, but more black, traite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and odious obligation and oath, was that of the abjuration, which moſt horridly did conjure the perjured ſwearers, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce their lawful King, and his royal line, and the ſucceſſors of that imperial and renowned family.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Sicut men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiri non po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test qui non loquitur, ſic pejerare non poterit qui jurare non appetit. D. Bernard ſer. <hi>32.</hi> de perjurio.</note>And this potion though dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and damnable like viper wine, went pleaſantly down with two ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, who if not ſoundly purged with true repentance, may feel the acerbity of this venemous compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition attended with pangs and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, in their gauled conſciences for ever. This was a treaſon of the higheſt degree, a fin of a great mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitude,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:58102:56"/>a daring crime, aiming pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digiouſly to deſtroy the roots, and branches of the royal ſtemm: and though it was hatcht and contriv'd by a cunning hypocritical Crocodile and his bloudy Sycophants;<note place="margin">Cromwel.</note> yet as if Heaven and Earth, God and man did abhor ſuch an odious oath and combination, how ſuddenly did it pleaſe God, that his arme of provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence ſhould appear and incline the hearts, not only of his loyal ſubjects but even of thoſe who had been bitter Enemies to the royal throne, to endeavour and cooperate for his Majeſties reſtauration. And now all theſe Withes and new Cords being broken by a <hi>Samſonian</hi> ſtrength and influence from true Soveraignty, are untwiſted and unravel'd to an <hi>odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um</hi> and a ſcorn. And the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hath judiciouſly and nobly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined and damn'd the covenant, the Engagement and the oath of Abjuration to be illegal, factious
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:58102:56"/>and ſeditious papers, and all ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ſubjects may ſecurely acquieſs in their judgement and determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.<note n="u" place="margin">Malum quod jura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus facere, non debe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus impl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> D. Ber. de perjur. ſer. <hi>32.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>If this <hi>Collyrium</hi> clear not the eyes of all Proteſters, Covenanters, Engagers and abjurators, nor all theſe reaſons reduce the phanati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally deluded to their fidelity and allegiance to their King: let them beware leaſt the judgement, as well as the ſins of deteſtable perjury follow, or fall upon them. This is a horrid crime, which the School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men lay open to the world in this dreſs, that<note n="x" place="margin">Perjuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um eſt mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacium ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramento. firmatum. Aurey, Theſ. Eccleſ. lib. <hi>4.</hi> diſt. <hi>39.</hi>
               </note> perjury is a ly confirm'd and ratified by an oath, and this is a moſt fearful aggravation. And it is St. <hi>Hieroms</hi> reſolution<note n="y" place="margin">Ius ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randum tres habet comites ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatem ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicium &amp; juſtitiam. Hieron. ſuper Hieremi. <hi>22.</hi> q. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> that no oath is lawful, unleſs it be attended, with three indiſpenſable concomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants. <hi>viz.</hi> Truth, Iudgement and Righteouſneſſe, and where all or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of theſe three faile, an oath is perjury, St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> is more ſtrict,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:58102:57"/>claring plainly<note n="z" place="margin">Cum ſit vel putat falſum eſſe &amp; tamen pro vero jurat D. Aug. de ver. Apoſt. ſer. <hi>28.</hi>
               </note> that he is perjured, that ſweareth voluntarily, what he knoweth to be falſe, with a deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful deſign, or if he perfectly know it not, thinketh it to be falſe. The Fathers make an out-cry, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim ſeverely againſt this crime, and call it <hi>Bellua deteſtanda,</hi> a moſt deteſtable beaſt, and filthy ſin. The ſchoolmen ſeem yet more ſevere then the Fathers<note n="a" place="margin">Iurans rerum, quod putat eſſe falſum, vel jurans fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum quod putat eſſe verum, eſt perjurus <hi>T.</hi> Aquin. <hi>22.</hi> ae. q. <hi>98, 1.3.</hi>
               </note> &amp; <hi>Aquinas</hi> deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mins that he who ſweareth the truth which he thinketh to be falſe, or ſwearing that which is falſe thinketh it to be truth, is a perjured perſon. Where the ſin is ſo notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, the infamy and obloquies ſo odious, and the judgements of the Eternal revenger, ſo terrible and dangerous againſt perjured perſons; how careful ſhould ſubjects be to recover themſelves to the duty of loyalty, and thereby to repair their credit and to vindicate themſelves from eternal plagues and infamy.</p>
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:58102:57"/>
            <p>The clouds thus diſperſed by the beams of truth, and rational argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. It is moſt evident that thoſe ſubjects who ſtarted from their alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance &amp; loyalty, can neither plead ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe or merit, for their tergiverſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on &amp; Apoſtacy, &amp; as to any unlawful oaths wherewith their ſoules were inſnared or intangled, they are by the ſupream laws of God &amp; the laws of men diſcharghed &amp; abſolved from them, unleſs hardned with obſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, they will as 'tis in the Greek proverb<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> i. e. malum ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo meditatur ſophocles &amp; Aeneas Platonicus.</note> ad ſin unto ſin, force one nail with driving another, and to perjury adde wilful impenitency, but better things may be hoped from all ſubjects, who as men look on them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as born for rational ſociety or as Chriſtians profeſſing the truths of ſacred religion, and not longer adhering to ſelf opinion, or ſediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous faction, be perfectly converted to be true cordial royaliſts: remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring the caution and counſel the
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:58102:58"/>late royal<note n="c" place="margin">Εικον Βασιλικε <hi>cont.</hi> 19. <hi>pag.</hi> 174.</note> Martyr gave, not to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend a reformation, and to force a rebellion, nor to hearken or give credit to thoſe paraſitick preachers who dared to call thoſe Martyrs, who dyed fighting againſt their King the laws, their oathes and the religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on eſtabliſhed. But ſober Chriſtians know that glorious title of Martyrs can with truth be applied to thoſe, who ſincerely preferred Gods truth and their duty in all particulars be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their lives, and all that was dear to them in this world, who where religiouſly ſenſible of thoſe tyes to God, the Church and the King, which lay on their ſouls, both for obedience and juſt aſſiſtance. By this time apoſtatiz'd and deluded ſubjects (their eyes being as well opened with ſad experience, as bright beames of reaſon and truth) may cleerly ſee their errours and more ſecurely avoid their dangers. But leaſt as thoſe who behold their
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:58102:58"/>faces in a glaſs, they may upon are<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moval utterly forget their features or complexions. It may not prove improper to ſet before us thoſe pure Chriſtals of Piety, Wiſdome, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, Honour and Government, which the cuſtomes and laws of former ages have conveyed to this preſent generation, engaging both the King and people to their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective dutyes, whereby the ſove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign and all his ſubjects are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended under <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>mental obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onds.<note n="d" place="margin">Fidelis ſermo reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net locum ſacramenti Iuramento non egit veritas D. Ber. Serm. <hi>32.</hi>
               </note> This difference and diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on only admitted that glorious Princes of the imperial Crown of <hi>England,</hi> have in their royal grace, and voluntary condeſcention ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed themſelves to ſolemn oathes at their coronation: but the Kings ſubjects are obliged by oaths ſetled, formed and confirmed by laws to exhibit and perform their homage, Fealty, allegiance and Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity to their Kings as Gods an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:58102:59"/>and in theſe high privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges and prerogatives, the Kings of <hi>England</hi> ſeem to have a more le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal tye and ſoveraignty, over their ſubjects, then either the Crown of <hi>France</hi> or <hi>Spain,</hi> whoſe ſubjects are commanded in greater vaſſalage, and as brighter and leading ſtars, that ſacred oathes &amp; obligations are here preſented, which pious Kings and Queens have accuſtomed to take at their coronation, when they ſealed to their ſacred vows, in the communion and ſacrament of the body and bloud of Chriſt; and then as better fitted, have laid their hands on the bleſſed Evangeliſts, bowing their heads have kiſſed the book, (the beſt eternal evidence of the affection of the heart) and thus prepared, they have uſually received the Imperial Crown and Scepter; with other <hi>Regalia</hi> and Emblems of royal Majeſtie from Gods altar, as holding all their power and ſove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:58102:59"/>from the King of Kings, and Lord of Lords, that God, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and Men, Heaven and Earth, and the whole world, and all ages to come, may behold the pious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity of Sacred Princes.</p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="oaths">
                  <body>
                     <div type="oath">
                        <head>The Kings Oath at his Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation </head>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>L. Biſhop of <hi>London.</hi>
                           </speaker>
                           <p>
                              <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR, will you grant and keep, and by your Oath confirm to the people of <hi>England,</hi> the Laws and Cuſtomes to them granted by the Kings of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> your lawful and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous predeceſſors; and namely the Laws, Cuſtomes &amp; Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſes granted to the Clergy,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:58102:60"/>by the glorious KING St. <hi>Edward</hi> your predeceſſour, according to the Laws of God, the true profeſſion of the Goſpel eſtabliſhed in this Kingdome, and agreeing to the prerogative of the Kings thereof, and the ancient cuſtomes of this Realm.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>The King.</speaker>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Igrant and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to keep them.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Lord Bishop.</speaker>
                           <p>Sir, will you keep peace and Godly agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment entirely according to your power both to God, the holy Church, the Clergy and the people.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <pb n="79" facs="tcp:58102:60"/>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>King.</speaker>
                           <p>
                              <hi>I will keep it.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>L. Bishop.</speaker>
                           <p>Sir, will you to your power cauſe law and juſtice and diſcretion in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and truth to be executed, in all your judgements.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>King.</speaker>
                           <p>
                              <hi>I will.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>L. Bishop.</speaker>
                           <p>Sir, will you grant to hold and keep the rightful Cuſtomes which the commonalty of this your Kingdome have? will you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend and uphold them to the honour of God ſo much as in you lyeth?</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>King.</speaker>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Igrant and promiſe ſo to do.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </sp>
                     </div>
                     <div type="oath">
                        <pb n="80" facs="tcp:58102:61"/>
                        <head>The Petition of the L. Biſhops read by the L. Biſhop of ROCHESTER.</head>
                        <p>O Lord our King, we beſeech you to grant and preſerve unto us, and the Churches committed to our charge, all Canonical priviledges, and due Law and Iuſtice; and that you would protect and defend us, as every good King in his Kingdome ought to be a Protector and defender of the Biſhops, and Churches under their Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>The King anſwered?</hi> With a willing and devout heart, I promiſe and grant my pardon, and that I will preſerve and maintain to you and the Churches committed to your charge, all Canonical priviledges and due law and juſtice, and that I will be your Protector and Defendor to my power, by the aſsistance of God, as every good
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:58102:61"/>King in his Kingdome, ought in right protect and defend the Biſhops and Churches under their Government.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Then the King went to the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar where laying his hand upon the Evangeliſts, he took the Oath following,</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The things which I have here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore promiſed, I ſhall perform &amp; keep, ſo God me help, and by the contents of this Book, and ſo kiſſed the Book.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="oath">
                        <pb n="82" facs="tcp:58102:62"/>
                        <head>The Homage of the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> for himſelf and all the Biſhops, (he kneel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down, and all the Biſhops behind him) ſaid,</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>I William</hi> Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> ſhall be faithful &amp; true, &amp; Faith &amp; Truth ſhall bear unto you our Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Lord, and your Heirs, Kings of <hi>England,</hi> and I ſhall do and truly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the ſervice of the Lands which I claim to hold of you, as in right of the Church, So God me help.</p>
                        <p>Then he aroſe and kiſſed the Kings left cheek, as did the reſt of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="oath">
                        <head>The Homage of the Nobility.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>I James</hi> Duke of <hi>York</hi> become your Leigeman of life and limb, and of earthly worſhip, and Faith and Truth I shall bear unto you, to live
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:58102:62"/>and dye againſt all manner of folk, So God me help.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="oath">
                        <head>The Oath of a Lord <hi>Chancelour.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>YOu ſhall ſwear that well and tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly you ſhall ſerve our Soveraign Lord the King, and his people in the office of Chancelour: and you ſhall do right to all manner of people, poor and rich, after the laws and uſages of this Realm, and truly you ſhall coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel the King, and his Counſel: you ſhall layne and keep, and you ſhall not know nor ſuffer the hurt or diſheriting of the King, or that the rights of the Crown be deceaſed by any means as far forth as you may let it: and if you may not let it, you ſhall make it cleerly and expreſly to be known un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the King, with your true advice and councel, and that you ſhall do and purchaſe the Kings profit in all that you reaſonably may. As God you help, and by the contents of this book.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="oath">
                        <pb n="84" facs="tcp:58102:63"/>
                        <head>The Oath of a privy Counceller.</head>
                        <p>YOu shall ſwear to be a true and faithful ſervant unto the Kings Majeſtie as one of his privy counſel, you ſhall not know or underſtand any manner of thing to be attempted, done or ſpoken againſt his Majeſties Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Honour, Crown or Dignity Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al: but you shall let and withſtand the ſame, to the utmoſt of your power, and either cauſe it to be revealed to his Majeſtie himſelf, or to ſuch of his privie Councel as shall advertiſe his Highneſs of the ſame. You shall in all things, to be moved, treated and debated in Councel, faithfully and tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declare your mind and opinion, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to your heart and conſcience, and shall keep ſecret all matters com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted and revealed unto you, or shall be treated off ſecretly in Counſel, and if any of the ſame Treaties or Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels ſhall touch any of the Councellers
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:58102:63"/>you ſhall not reveale it unto him, but ſhall keep the ſame until ſuch time, as by the conſent of his Majeſty or of the Councel, publication shall be made thereof. You ſhall to your uttermoſt bear Faith and Allegiance unto the Kings Majeſtie, his Heirs, and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſucceſſours, and shall aſsist and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend all jurisdictions, preheminences, and authorities granted to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie and annexed to his Crown, againſt all forraign Princes, Perſons, Prelates and Potentates, by act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament or otherwiſe. And generally in all things you shall do as a faithful and true ſervant and Subject ought to do to his Majeſtie: So help you God and by the holy contents of this book.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="oath">
                        <head>The Oath of a Secretary of State.</head>
                        <p>YOu ſhal ſwear to be a true &amp; faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Servant unto the Kings Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie, as one of the Principal Secretaries
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:58102:64"/>of State to his Majestie: you ſhall not know or underſtand of any manner of thing to be attempted, done or ſpoken againſt his Majeſties perſon, Honour, Crown or Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity-royal, but you ſhall let and withſtand the ſame to the uttermoſt of your power, and either do, or cauſe it to be revealed, either to his Majeſtie himſelf or to his pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie Counſel, you ſhall keep ſecret all mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters revealed and committed unto you, or that ſhall be ſecretly treated in Counſel, and if any of the ſaid treaties or Counſels ſhall touch any of the Councellors, you ſhall not reveal the ſame unto him, but ſhall keep the ſame until ſuch time as by the conſent of his Majeſtie, or the Conn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, publication ſhall be made thereof; you ſhall to your uttermoſt bear Faith and Allegiance to the Kings Majeſtie, his heirs and lawful ſucceſſours, and ſhall aſſiſt and defende all jurisdictions, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heminences and authorities granted to his Majestie and annexed to his Crown,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:58102:64"/>against all forraign Princes, Perſons, Prelats or Potentates, &amp;c. By act of Parliament or otherwiſe, &amp; Generally in all things you ſhall do as a true and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſervant and ſubject ought to do to his Majeſtie. So help you God, and by the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contents of this book.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="oath">
                        <p>
                           <hi>Subſcription of ſuch as are to be made Miniſters according to the 37 canon and conſtitution,</hi> Anno Dom. <hi>1603. and in the reign of our Soveraign Lord</hi> Iames, <hi>by the grace of God King of</hi> England, Scotland, France <hi>and</hi> Ireland <hi>the firſt, and of</hi> Scotland <hi>the 37. in the Synod begun at</hi> London.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>No perſon shall hereafter be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived into the Miniſtry, nor either by inſtitution or collation admitted to any Eccleſiaſtical living, or by the Arch-Bishop or Bishop of the Dioceſs, except he shall firſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe to theſe three Articles in ſuch
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:58102:65"/>ſort and manner as we have here appointed.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <div n="1" type="article">
                           <head>Article. I.</head>
                           <p>That the Kings Majeſtie under God is the only ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Governour of this Realm, and of all other his Highneſs Dominions and Countries, as well in all ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual or eccleſiaſtical things, or cauſes, as temporal: and that noforrain Prince, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Prelat or Potentate have or ought to have any juris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, power, ſuperiority, preheminence or authority, Eccleſiaſtical or Spiritual, within his Majeſties ſaid
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:58102:65"/>Realmes, Dominions and Countries.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="2" type="article">
                           <head>Article II.</head>
                           <p>That the book of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-prayer, and of orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of Biſhops, Prieſts and Deacons, containeth nothing in it contrary to the word of God, and that it may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully be uſed, and that he himſelf will uſe the form in the ſaid book preſcribed, in publick prayer and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of the Sacraments, and none other.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="3" type="article">
                           <pb n="90" facs="tcp:58102:66"/>
                           <head>Article III.</head>
                           <p>That he alloweth the book of Articles of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on agreed upon by the Arch-Biſhops and Biſhops of both Provinces, and the whole Clergy in the convocation held at <hi>London,</hi> in the year of our Lord God one thouſand five hundred ſixty and two, and that he acknowledgeth all and every the Articles therein contained, being in number nine an thirty, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the Ratification to be agreable to the word of God.</p>
                           <pb n="91" facs="tcp:58102:66"/>
                        </div>
                     </div>
                     <div type="oath">
                        <head>The form of words, to avoid all ambiguities, followeth <hi>viz.</hi> Setting down his Chriſtian and Surname.</head>
                        <p>I, <hi>N. N.</hi> do willingly and <hi>ex Animo,</hi> ſubſcribe to theſe three <hi>Articles</hi> above mentioned, and to all things contained in them.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="oath">
                        <head>An Oath againſt Symony, at in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution into Benifices,</head>
                        <p>I <hi>N. N.</hi> do ſwear that I have made no ſymonical payment,<note place="margin">Can. 40.</note> contract or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, directly or indirectly, by my ſelf, or any other to my knowledge, or with my conſent, to any perſon or
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:58102:67"/>perſons whatſoever, for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning and obtaining this ecclefiaſtical dignity, place, preferment, office or li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, <hi>(reſpectively and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly naming the ſame, whereunto he is to be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, inſtituted, collated, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtalled or confirmed,)</hi> nor will at any time hereafter perform or ſatisfie any ſuch kind of payment, contract or promiſe made by any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther without my knowledg or conſent, So help me God, through Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="oath">
                        <p>And as the Clergy are obliged to ſubſcribe <hi>ex Animo</hi> to the three Articles contained in the 37 canon,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:58102:67"/>ſo are they (when they receive holy orders, and are made Deacons or Prieſts, at their ordination, or when they receive inſtitution to any Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Living or Promotion, and Inſtallation to any Dignity in the Church) obliged to canonical obedience, to their reſpective Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſans, and the Biſhops likewiſe are (at their conſecrations) obliged to promiſe Canonical obedience, to their Metropolitans, and the reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pective Arch-Biſhops of either Provinces and Sees of <hi>Canterbury</hi> and <hi>York:</hi> and the Arch-Biſhops likewiſe promiſe and vow the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes of Faith and true Allegiance to the King, when (at their homage, kneeling before the King) they take an Oath of Fealty and Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the King, and his lawful heirs and ſucceſſors.</p>
                        <p>Theſe are moſt holy and ſacred<note n="d" place="margin">Iura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum eſt confirmatio verbi; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quo jura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. <hi>Orig.</hi>
                           </note> bonds, more fit for all the Sonnes of <hi>Aaron</hi> and the Tribe of <hi>Levy,</hi> and
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:58102:68"/>Theſe do breed, keep and cheriſh Peace &amp; unity in the Church;<note n="e" place="margin">Quid eſt jurare per Deum nifi teſtis eſt Deus? D. August de verbis Apoſtoli ſermn. <hi>28.</hi>
                           </note> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige the inferiour orders to their ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours; &amp; in fine, unite all eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtick ſubjects in true Allegiance to their King. And though the Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts and ſome ſquemiſh Phanaticks, (cunningly inſtructed, or factiouſly engaged) are ſhy of ſuch ſacred oaths and obligations: yet, it is warranted from the holy Scripture. Thus <hi>Abimelech</hi> and <hi>Phicol</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired an Oath from <hi>Abraham,</hi>
                           <note place="margin">
                              <hi>Gen.</hi> 21.23.</note> 
                           <hi>Now therefore ſwear unto me here by God, that thou wilt not deal falſly with me, nor with my Son, nor with my Sonns Son.</hi> Thus <hi>Moſes</hi> directeth <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
                           <note n="f" place="margin">
                              <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.13.10.12.13.4.</note> 
                           <hi>Thou shalt fear the Lord thy God and ſerve him, and ſwear by his name.</hi> Thus<note n="g" place="margin">
                              <hi>Ezra.</hi> 10.5.</note> 
                           <hi>Ezra aroſe and made the cheif Priests, the Levites, and all Iſrael to ſwear, that they ſhould do according to this word: and they ſware.</hi> And if yet, any deluded or factious Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity, be not ſatisfied, but will
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:58102:68"/>object evangelical ſtrict Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands againſt lawful Oathes: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Chriſt hath preached<note n="h" place="margin">Matt. 5.34. 1 Iam. 5.12.</note> 
                           <hi>Swear not at all:</hi> and St. <hi>Iames</hi> adviſed,<note n="k" place="margin">Hanc eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randi, peſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuetudinem habere Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daeinoſcun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. <hi>D. Hiero.</hi> in <hi>5. Mat.</hi>
                           </note> 
                           <hi>above all things (my brethren ſwear not.)</hi> Yet theſe ſacred Cautions and Commands, were not to take away the lawful and holy, but the unlawful and profane uſe and cu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtome of Oathes. Thus St. <hi>Hierom</hi> commenteth. Our Saviour doth not utterly forbid an Oath, <hi>ſed per coelum &amp; terram jurare!</hi> St. <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> ſeems more full and plain, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that Counſel was given to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent an idle and ſinful habit of ſwear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; which from a profane facility, might quickly run into cuſtome, and ſo fall into perjury; or, that no perſons ſhould be affected with cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomary Oathes or ſwearing;<note n="k" place="margin">Dico vobis non jurare om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nino, ne ſcil. juran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do ad facili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randi Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventatur, &amp; en fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultate ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randi ad conſeitudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem &amp; à conſuetudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne in Perju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datur. <hi>D. Auguſt.</hi> de menda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio, cap. <hi>15.</hi>
                           </note> or greedily with delight and dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation to ſeek and hunt after Oathes, which on good grounds may be lawful: and for a good end
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:58102:69"/>and purpoſe, to diſcern truth, and to end all Controverſies; And thus St. <hi>Paul</hi> (on ſeveral occaſions) hath preſented himſelf an Apoſtolical exemplar to Gods Church. And to all that hath been ſaid, it may be further added. That it is a Theolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical determination of the Church of <hi>England;</hi>
                           <note n="l" place="margin">Articles of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. 39. Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle.</note> to which every true ſonne hath or ought to ſubſcribe and ſubmit. <hi>That as vain and raſh ſwearing is forbidden Chriſtian men by our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and Iames his Apoctle: ſo we judge that Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion doth not prohibit, but that a man may ſwear, when the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate requireth, in a cauſe of faith and charity. So it be done according to the Prophets teaching, in Iuſtice, Iudgement and Truth.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="oaths">
                        <pb n="97" facs="tcp:58102:69"/>
                        <head>The Oath of <hi>Allegiance</hi> and <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy;</hi> enjoined by order of Parliament.</head>
                        <div type="oath">
                           <head>The Oath of <hi>Allegiance.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <p>I A. B. <hi>Do truly and ſincerely acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, profeſſe, testifie and declare in my conſcience before God and the world, that our Soveraign Lord King</hi> Charles <hi>is lawful and rightful King of this Realm, and of all other his Majesties Dominions and Countries; and that the Pope, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of himſelf, nor by any authority of the Church or See of Rome, or by any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther means with any other, hath any power or authority to depoſe the King, or to diſpoſe any of his Majeſties Kingdomes or Dominions, or to authoriſe any Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Prince to invade or annoy him or his. Countries, or to diſcharge any of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of their Allegiance and obedience to his Majeſty, or to give licenſe or leave to any of them to bear Arms, raiſe Tumults, or to offer any violence or hurt to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Royal Perſon, State or Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or to any of his Majeſties Subjects within his Majeſties Dominions.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <pb n="98" facs="tcp:58102:70"/>
                           <p>Alſo I do ſwear from my heart, that notwithſtanding any Declaration or ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Excommunication or Deprivation made or granted, or to be made or grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Pope or his Succeſſours, or by any Authority derived or pretended to be derived from him or his See, againſt the ſaid King, his Heirs or Succeſſours, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Abſolution of the ſaid Subjects from their Obedience; I will bear Faith and true Allegiance to his Majeſty, his Heirs and Succeſsours, and him and them will defend to the uttermoſt of my power, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all conſpiracies and attempts what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever which ſhall be made againſt his or their Perſons, their Crown and Dignity, by reaſon or colour of any ſuch Sentence or Declaration or otherwiſe; and will do my beſt endeavour to diſcloſe and make known unto his Majeſty, his Heirs and Succeſſours, all Treaſons and Trayterous Conſpiracies which I ſhall know or hear of, to be againſt him or any of them.</p>
                           <p>And I do further ſwear, That I do from my heart abhor, deteſt and abjure, as impious and heretical, this Damnable Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and Poſition, That princes which be excommunicated or deprived by the Pope, may be depoſed or murthered by their
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:58102:70"/>Subjects, or any other whatſoever.</p>
                           <p>And I do believe and in conſcience am reſolved, that neither the Pope nor any perſon whatſoever hath power to abſolve me of this Oath, or any part thereof which I acknowledge by good and full Authority to be lawfully adminiſtred unto me, and do renounce all pardons and diſpenſations to the contrary. And all theſe things I doe plainly and ſincerely acknowledge, &amp; ſwear according to theſe expreſse words by me ſpoken, and according to the plain and common ſenſe and underſtanding of the ſame words, without any equivocation, or mental evaſion, or ſecret reſervation what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever: And I do make this Recognition and acknowledement heartily, willingly and truly, upon the true faith of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian. <hi>So help me God,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="oath">
                           <head>The Oath of <hi>Supremacy.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <p>I A. B. <hi>Do utterly teſtifie and declare in my conſcience, that the</hi> King<hi>'s High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is the onely Supream Governour of this Realm, and of all other his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſse's Dominions and Countries, as well in all Spiritual or Eccleſiaſtical things or cauſes as Temporal; And that no Foreign
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:58102:71"/>Prince, Perſon, Prelate, State or Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, hath or or ought to have any Juris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, Power, Superiority, Preeminence or Authority Eccleſiaſtical or Spiritual within this Realm: And therefore I do utterly renounce and forſake all Forraign Jurisdictions, Powrs, Superiorities and Authorities, and do promiſe that from henceforth I ſhall bear Faith and true Allegiance to the</hi> King's <hi>Highneſſe, his Heirs and lawfull Succeſſours, and to my power ſhall aſſiſt and defend all Jurisdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Priviledges, Preeminences and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities granted, or belonging to the</hi> Kings <hi>Highneſs, his Heirs and ſucceſſours or united and annexed to the Imperial Crown of this Realm.</hi> So help me God, and by the contents of this book.</p>
                           <p>Theſe Platforms and models of Oathes, as they are of holy uſe to unite our fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity to God and Man, ſo they are of Divine Authority, and ſeem to be influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ential from Heaven, from whence we have the Sacred example; ſo the Scriptures teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie. Exod, 33.1. <hi>Depart hence un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Land which I ſwear unto</hi> Abraham Iſaac <hi>and</hi> Jacob. Thus divine uſage is very frequent with God. Deut 1.8.34.35.
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:58102:71"/>Pſal. 95.9. Luk. 1.73. Heb. 6.13. Heb. 7.21. <hi>And as God pleaſed to confirm his promiſe with an Oath. So King</hi> David <hi>Gods an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed voweth and ſweareth, calling on God and praying, Lord remember</hi> David <hi>and all his Afflictions, how he ſwear un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord and vowed to the mighty God of</hi> Jacob. Pſal. 132.1. 2. And <hi>Solomon</hi> his royal Son gave Counſel to all his ſubjects, and all the world. <hi>I counſel thee to keep the Kings commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and that in regard of the Oath of God.</hi> Eccleſ. 8.2.</p>
                        </div>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>Having now ſet fourth the ſacred ☜ Oaths and obligations of the Kings and Queens of <hi>England,</hi> and of ſome of the cheif Officers and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of State, together with the Homage of the Eccleſiaſtical Hi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rarchy, and temporal Nobility, and of the three great Officers of Court: the Lord high Steward, the Maſter of the Horſe, and the Lord Chamberlain, by their Oathes as privy counſellors under, whoſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:58102:72"/>command and power, all ſervants at Court, are ſworn to fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and obedience, in their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective relations, and ranks of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, degrees and ſubordinations. It is plain and eaſie to every rational ſubject to diſcern and ſee the moſt excellent form of Government that the prudence and piety of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ages hath conveyed to the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh to this preſent time: and we cannot do leſs then admire and magnifie the gracious providence, and riches of Gods favours to the Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> who hath with the golden chain of harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious Government ſo lincked Kings and Queens to himſelf, and all their ſubjects and people to their ſove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Princes, that no Kingdome under the canopy of Heaven, hath a better frame of Government, either for Church or State, or the tranſaction of Eccleſiaſtick or civil concernments and affaires, in which
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:58102:72"/>there is ſuch an incementing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catenation by wholeſome laws, and cuſtomes, for juſtice, and the happy preſervation of all the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples Rights, that as the King may ſit as happily and ſecurely on his Throne as any Monarch on earth, ſo his people may as proſperouſly thrive under his gracious Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and repoſing themſelves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their own vines and figtrees; as cheerfully enjoy the ineſtimable bleſſings of their own juſt rights, and labours, Milk and Hony, with the overflowing favours of Peace and Plenty. How great a crime muſt it then be, to wreſt or break one of the invaluable lincks of this golden concatenation, which So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign Princes graciouſly pleaſe to ſtrengthen and conſolidate (if poſſible) by their ſacred Oathes to God, which cannot but indear and more oblige ingenuous ſubjects to greater exactneſs of duty and fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:58102:73"/>conſidering that theſe pious proceeding, are more acts of Grace and voluntary and Princely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcentions flowing from the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines of their own royal goodneſs, being methods of high degrees of kindneſs and love; where words or promiſes, and thoſe at their roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al wills and pleaſure, are to be look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on, not only as certainties and aſſurances, but as deeds and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat performances. The civil Law expecteth as much from No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble men, and Perſons of Honour, that there words be equally eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as their deeds,<note n="m" place="margin">Promiſſa nobilinm pro factis habentur. And Iſer. c. <hi>1.</hi> Tantum fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dei &amp; lega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litatis pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumitur in Nobilibus ut ſi quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſerint id per equeſit certum ac indubita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ac ſi jam factum eſſet. And Iſer. c, <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> thus <hi>Homer</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norably mentions <hi>Agamemnon</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Homer. Iliad. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> the word was no ſooner out of that great worthies mouth, but it was his act and deed, but Princes are of more ſublime and higher qualities as being earthly Gods, their words are more Sacred and Soveraign. Thus <hi>Pylat</hi> though an inferiour Potentate, toul'd the
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:58102:73"/>Jews, <hi>quod ſcripſi, ſcripſi.</hi> And <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vius</hi> commenting on thoſe words of the Poet<note n="o" place="margin">Virgil. lib. <hi>12.</hi> Aeneid.</note> 
               <hi>Do, quod vis, bene in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit, preſenti uſus eſt tempore: nam promiſsio in Diis pro facto eſt.</hi> I give what thou wilt, the God did well to uſe the preſent tenſe, as if the will and words of Princes were very Acts and Deeds, but if any knot can binde faſter then words or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, ſee the gracious diſpoſitions and cuſtomes of the Kings of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> offering up (as in the beauty of holineſs,) the ſacrifice of pious reſolutions to God Almighty, in ſacred oathes for their moſt Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly government.</p>
            <p>And as Kings thus unite them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. by theſe moſt Sacred bonds to the King of Kings, ſo their Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers and Miniſters of State, and ſervants of their Courts, are engaged by ſpecial Oathes of Obedience and Fidelity, and all their ſubjects are obliged by a national Law, to ſwear
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:58102:74"/>to the Oathes of Allegiance and Supremacy, no rank being to be excuſed (at the age of Eighteen) from theſe juſt and rational obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, unleſs the Lords and Peers of the Realm, whoſe refined Honour being as equivalent, if not more ſuperlative, doth as powerfully in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dear them to loyalty and true alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance to their Princes; it cannot then but be juſtly cenſured a crime of the higheſt nature to violate ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred bonds with treachery and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelity; and yet that ſoul ſin may be preſented more ugly, when any in greater and neerer truſt about the King, (as a Miniſter of his roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al affairs, or a ſworn ſervant of his Court) ſhall perfidiouſly or timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly forfeit his Faith, which by duplicated Oathes being ſealed on his Soul, as a door more ſecure un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a double lock ought to be more firm, and not to be forced by any Art or Engine: and if ſingle per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:58102:74"/>be ſo notorious a crime, how horrid and helliſh will it appear in the multiplication of falſe illegal &amp; perjurous and damnable Oathes.</p>
            <p>The link and jonts of govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, thus reaching from Heaven to Eatth, from God to Man, and from the King of Kings to Kings and Princes on earth, they thence graciouſly deſcend from royal thrones, to the meaneſt and loweſt of all their people: who in a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity participate of the bleſſings of Monarchy, under the protection and Grace of their Prince, and the benefit and proviſion of moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent and wholeſom laws, againſt whoſe ſacred Perſon (as being Gods annointed) or rules of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, if any ſhould be ſo trait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous or ſeditious, as to dare to contrive or conſpire, they merit the ſevereſt degrees of puniſhment, and though they be as near to the Crown in blood as <hi>Abſalon</hi> to
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:58102:75"/>King <hi>David,</hi> or as near in truſt and Counſels, as the grand oraculous politician <hi>Achitophel,</hi> yet no rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or employment can ſo palliat the blakneſſe of their offences, but that all good ſubjects are obliged as <hi>Huſhai</hi> the <hi>Archite,</hi> to preſerve their Prince in his royal Crown and dignity, and to detect and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover, diſſipate and deſtroy all treacherous conſpiraces, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious Treaſons againſt their Prince. This was the reſolution and adventure of Noble <hi>Huſhai,</hi> who commanded by King <hi>David</hi> obeyed his royal pleaſure, and leaving the King in a deplorable ſad condition, addreſſed to the uſurper and traitor <hi>Abſalon,</hi> and ſeemingly confederated with that unnatural Arch Traitor, and <hi>Achitophel</hi> and his complices; but God had ſo ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed that this loyal ſubject, by his wiſdom and fidelity intrapped <hi>Abſalon</hi> to his merited ruine, and ſo
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:58102:75"/>infatuated the Councels of <hi>Achito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phel,</hi> that the deſpairing Traitor (hanging himſelf,) became his own executioner, and the rebellious ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my being routed, and totally defeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and <hi>Abſalon</hi> hanged by the head in a tree, King <hi>David</hi> was gloriouſly reſtored to the royal City of <hi>Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But leaſt any preſume to be loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all <hi>Huſhites,</hi> who cannot reaſonably merit the opinion or Name of true Royaliſts, and ſo not prove King <hi>Davids</hi> friends. It is neceſſary that ſome characters and diſtinctions be intermitted for cleerer truth, and plainer perſpicuiry of what is droſs, what is ſophiſticated falſe and fain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed mettal, and what (in this point) by the impartial touch ſtone is judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed pure and perfect gold.</p>
            <p>The ſtory of this concernment is a ſacred record, written by the holy Prophet <hi>Samuel,</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">2 Sam. 15.</note> which deſcribes King <hi>Davids</hi> danger and delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:58102:76"/>his enemies and his friends, preſents to the world the undutiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of an unnatural Son, and the rebellious attempts of ambitious and traiterous ſubjects, <hi>Abſalon</hi> was the Arch traitor, and <hi>Achitophel</hi> the cheif Counſelour in this foul con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy and black Treaſon, and the Prophet (as if to forewarn the world from future deluſion and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fatuation of that kind) deſcribes the Traitors and Conſpirators.<note place="margin">Traiterous crimes or marks, 1. defamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or detracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> Firſt, defaming and diſhonoring the Kings government, ſowing ſedition, and diſgracing the royal Courts of Iuſtice, ſaying, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.3. <hi>See, ſaith</hi> Abſolon, <hi>thy matters be good and right, but there is no man deputed of the King to hear thee.</hi> This de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign was countenanced with the pompe and pride of a popular train. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.1. to amaze or allure the vulgar,<note place="margin">2 Popular pompe &amp; pride.</note> Abſolon <hi>prepared Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riots and Horſes, and fifty men to run before him.</hi> A great pretence to
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:58102:76"/>execute judgement,<note place="margin">3 A pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to do juſtice and execute judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> and do juſtice, promoted this rebellion, ſo the grand Impoſtor made way to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance his rebellion ſaying 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.4. <hi>O that I were made Iudge in the land, that every man that hath any ſuite or cauſe might come unto me,</hi> (as the Supream Magiſtrate and cheif Iuſtice) <hi>And I would do him justice,</hi>
               <note place="margin">4 Reſtleſs watching day and night.</note> vigilancy, diligence and indefatiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble induſtry and attendance; to ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſs and court the people, were active practiſes of this popular po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litician ſo <hi>Samuel</hi> ſets forth the traitour in the 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.2. Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon <hi>roſe up early and ſtood beſide the way of the Gate,</hi>
               <note place="margin">5 Flattery and adulation.</note> 
               <hi>and when any man that had a controvercy came to the King for judgement, then</hi> Abſolon <hi>called unto him,</hi> and with oily court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip quickly deluded common ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacities, and ſimple credulity: this venemous and traiterous infatua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that ſo ſwelled the people with avarice and ambition, was as
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:58102:77"/>epidemick and national, as infecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and inſnaring,<note place="margin">6 Traite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection is uſually epidmical</note> 
               <hi>For, on this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner did</hi> Abſolon <hi>to all</hi> Iſrael <hi>that came to the King for judgement.</hi> 2 Sam. 15.6. Traitors uſually pules every vain, try all tempers, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline all humours to augment and corroberate their party, and to effectuate their evil contrivances and machinations,</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">7 Traitors are moſt courty crafty and fulleſt of diſſimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note>And as traitors lay their plots and deſigns, for general advantages, ſo they bend and humble themſelves to court and catch all capacities. Thus <hi>Cataline</hi> careſſed the loweſt of the Romans as he paſſed in the ſtreets. And it is remarkable in <hi>Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> how like a Serpent he inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, creeping and cringing, bend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and bowing to the earth; ſo the Prophet obſerves him in his cariage to the meaneſt <hi>Iſraelite,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.5. <hi>And it was ſo that when any man came nigh to him, to do him obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance, he put forth his hand and took
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:58102:77"/>him and kiſſed him.</hi> But that which was the cheifeſt cheat,<note place="margin">8 Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie or the holy cheat</note> and both deluded King <hi>David</hi> and his ſubjects, was cunning hypocriſy, or (in the abuſed canting phraiſe of theſe jugling times) Liberty of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and a pretence to holineſſe, or performance of religious vows; ſo the Prophet deſcribes the decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.7.8, <hi>And it came to paſse after forty years that</hi> Abſolon <hi>ſaid unto the King, I pray thee let me go and pay my vow, which I have vowed unto the Lord in</hi> He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bron, <hi>for thy ſervant vowed a vow while I abode at</hi> Geſhur <hi>in</hi> Syria, <hi>ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing if the Lord ſhall bring me again indeed to</hi> Ieruſalem, <hi>then I will ſerve the Lord.</hi> And as this arch conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator <hi>Abſolon,</hi> ſo his councellor <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chitophel</hi> ſeemd to be very zealous, and religious: ſo the Prophet taketh notice that <hi>Achitophel</hi> being ſent for by <hi>Abſolon, He was it his City of</hi> Giloh <hi>where he was raiſing rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:58102:78"/>when offering ſacrifices.</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.12, There were many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands engaged and envolved in the ☞ conſpiracy, and ſome few hundred more innocent, or rather leſs mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Traitors: and the Prophet to their comfort recordeth both their number and their qualities, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.11. <hi>And with</hi> Abſolon <hi>went two hundred men out of</hi> Ieruſalem, <hi>that were called, and they went in their ſimplicity, and they knew not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing.</hi>
               <note place="margin">9 Traitors are falſe and moſt perſidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</note> There is yet one atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant more, that is concomitant and adherent to traiterous diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which are for the moſt part, very falſe and horridly perfidious; thus <hi>Abſolon</hi> had no ſooner leave to go <hi>in peace to</hi> Hebron, <hi>but imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately he ſent his ſpies through all the tribes of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>ſaying, as ſoon as ye hear the ſound of the Trumpet, then ye ſhall ſay</hi> Abſolon <hi>reigneth in</hi> He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bron, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.10. Theſe nine characters whiles they conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:58102:78"/>engraven on traiterous ſubjects hearts; they cannot be permitted to the reputation of true royaliſts, as <hi>Huſhai</hi> the <hi>Archite,</hi> that noble <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lite,</hi> who was not tainted with any of theſe defiling qualities, but po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitively and in the affirmative was richly endued with many heroick virtues, which did highly capacitate his noble ſoul, for the ſervice of his God the God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and for <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> the King the Lords annointed, and for the Peace, Liberty and Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of the Kingdome and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, where he was an honourable Courtier, a prudent Counſellour, a loyal ſubject, and faithful Patriot; and the holy pen of that ſacred wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, who did ſet forth &amp; character <hi>Abſolon, Achitophel</hi> and their traiterous confederates, doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineate and portray in moſt (lively colours) the moſt incomparable and ſupereminent virtues of the true and perfect royaliſt in the great
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:58102:79"/>abilities and worth of <hi>Huſhai</hi> the <hi>Archite,</hi> who (ſaith the Prophet) was in zealous paſſion,<note place="margin">Characters of true royaliſts. 1 Holy indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for their King in a ſad conditon. 2 Sam. 15.32.</note> or holy indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to ſee his King in a ſad condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, his people in rebellion, and the whole Kingdome in ſuch a wild confuſion and diſtraction, <hi>Ecce oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currit ei Chuſai Arachites, ſciſſâ veſte &amp; terrâ pleno capite. Behold</hi> Huſhai <hi>the</hi> Archite <hi>came to meet the King with his coat rent, and earth upon his head.</hi> Good ſubjects they neither value liberty,<note place="margin">2 Attend there Prince in greateſt danger.</note> life or limb, riches or fortune, nor any perſonal concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; but when their King and his Crown is in danger, and his royal Perſon in the field, they hazard and adventure all; as loyal ſubjects in their Princes ſervice, and they are not only to attend, but to be active, quick and lively in the concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a Crown: this great worthy is a noble example of diligence and activeneſs in his ſwift endeavours, to advance his princes cauſe, their
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:58102:79"/>is no mention made of declaration or proclamation, of the call of a drum or ſound of trumpet, but as ſoon as the royal Standaris mount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,<note place="margin">3 True royaliſts ought to be quick and active for their King in danger.</note> and it is but whiſpered, or at leaſt but rumourd that King <hi>David</hi> was in danger, and his people in rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, <hi>Huſhai</hi> ſpeedily poſteth and addreſſeth to the royal camp, ſo the Prophet expreſſeth, <hi>Chuſhai Arachi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes occurrit,</hi> ran (as with all haſte) <hi>to meet the King,</hi> impatient until he came to his Princes aid and aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. This worthy <hi>Iſraelite</hi> was neither timorouſly or cowardly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clind, as ignoble <hi>Poultrones,</hi> nor treacherouſly affected as <hi>Laodicean</hi> newters, nor ſhackled and impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned with the fetters of baſe and filthy luſts, as lacivious and lu xuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous epicures, but, as on a ſuddain a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandoning and quitting all delights prophits and concernments; as ſwift as lightning, he flyeth to attend his Prince in his dangerous extremities,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:58102:80"/>as <hi>Huſhai</hi> was quick and active for the preſervation of his King:<note place="margin">4 The beſt royaliſts the moſt religious. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Plato in Apol.</hi> 2 Sam. 15.32. <hi>Iſta ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orum ſcabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es ut omnes diſputare malint quam vive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve.</hi> Seneca epiſt. 2.5.</note> ſo he appeares (which was his greater honour and commendation,) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious, and rightly ſetled for his principles in Gods worſhip and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; he was no black ſoul'd Atheiſt, whoſe devotion intirely attends his intereſt, nor factious Schiſmatick, hypocritical ſeparatiſt, or brain ſick Phanatick, but a true <hi>Iſraelite</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed; and ſo it appears, by the double circumſtances of the manner and time of his attendance; for the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner it was in a Iewiſh mode and dreſs, his cloathes rent, and his head covered with earth, emblems of ſorrow and indignation, and a reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious condolement and compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And as to the time of his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs, it proved either by deſign or providence to be at that inſtant, <hi>When the King was come to the top of the Mount, where he worſhipped God, behold</hi> Huſhai <hi>the</hi> Archite <hi>came
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:58102:80"/>to meet him.</hi> Even then when the King was at his prayers and earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſaid,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 15.31.</note> 
               <hi>O Lord I pray thee turn the Counſel of</hi> Achitophel <hi>into fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſse.</hi>
               <note place="margin">5 Fortitude requisie in true royaliste.</note> Then as joyning in holy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, did <hi>Huſhai</hi> moſt happily at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend his Kings commands. To theſe excellent capacities and fitneſs, King <hi>David</hi> found <hi>Huſhai</hi> a man of cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age &amp; magnanimity, neither fearing the Enemies power, nor diſtruſting the Kings more weak and ſad con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, not of a low and puſillani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous ſpirit, nor of a ranting and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poring humour, who like ſome ſquibs and crackers will thunder and roare like lyons, (and though the cauſe be never ſo good) in an inſtant change their notes, and like timorus Hares betake themſelves to there heels. This <hi>Iſraelite</hi> was a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of honour and courage, truly valiant,<note place="margin">6 Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance requiſite in all royaliſts,</note> and therefore more proper for ſervice of higheſt truſt, and as this bright ſhining virtue did ſhew it
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:58102:81"/>ſelf in <hi>Huſhai;</hi> ſo temperance (doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe) kept him company, without whoſe influence underſtanding, ſence and reaſon, or what can be thought honorable to a Prince, will ſuddenly be drowned and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed in the ſtinking puddles of gluttony, drunkenneſſe, ryot, lux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ury, or deteſtable debaucheries. Temperance and valour, loves to keep company with juſtice; And 'tis very probable that this golden rule of doing right, and giving to every man his due, was a chief mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to King <hi>David</hi> to employ one of ſo juſt and righteous reſolutions,<note place="margin">7 Iuſtice and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right dealing.</note> who ſo dutifully paying his loyalty to his Prince as ſo cheerfully to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard and adventure his life, might (poſſibly) be more ſuccesful in ſo near a concernment as the preſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a King on his Throne, and the appeaſing and extinguiſhing of the flames of ſo formidable a trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. Theſe three fair Ladies are
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:58102:81"/>never without the ſociety and counſel of Prudence,<note place="margin">8 Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,</note> and in this pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rillous juncture ſhe might be more highly uſeful, becauſe as <hi>Plato,</hi> ſhe is the cheifeſt guide that beſt advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth humain actions.<note n="q" place="margin">Pruden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia ſola prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it &amp; ducit ad recte faciendum. Plato in menae.</note> 
               <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> is more plain urging<note n="r" place="margin">Fieri non poteſt ut quiſquam vere probus ſine pruden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia audiat. Arist. &amp; hic.</note> that no man can be juſtly ſtiled good or honeſt, who is not prudent, as neceſſary to true Policy and Government, as the line and plummet to the skilful <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chitect</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Vt Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chitectis nullum e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus recte proceſſcrit ſine libella &amp; I. Lipſ,</note>. This as the rudder turnes the Ship and beſt ſteers the courſe when ſhe is under ſaile: the King experiencing a quick and lively ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, a great judgement and more ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid underſtanding in his loyal ſubject the <hi>Archite,</hi> reſolved to make choice of his faithful abilities, when his Crown and life and all that was ſoveraign and truly royal, ſeemed to be in an ambiguous and dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous ſtate. To all theſe the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy, the fidelity, the ſecreſie, the extraordinary friendſhip, paſſionate
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:58102:82"/>love and amity, that King <hi>David</hi> had for <hi>Huſhai,</hi> or that <hi>Huſhai</hi> had for the perſon and high calling of the King: theſe happy experiences might rationally incline King <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> confidence,<note place="margin">9 Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy, Fidelity, Secreſy are requiſite in true loyaliſts.</note> to recommend and commiſſionate his faithful ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to manage and conduct this weighty buſineſs. Theſe are lively marks of true loyaliſts, and well worthy and becoming the imitation of all who pretend to be loyal ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects; yet this caſe of <hi>Huſhai</hi> ſeems to be of a moſt remarkable and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary quality, both in reſpect of King <hi>David</hi> and in relation to <hi>Huſhai.</hi> Firſt, in regard of the King, who (ſurpriſed with a rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, under a pretence of Religion, and a vow to be performed at <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bron</hi>) was forced to a ſuddain ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, to uſe his greateſt Art and Policy to diſperſe and diſſolve that growing traiterous cloud which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to ſpread, and to look ſo formi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable.
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:58102:82"/>Thus a great Critick ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventures to comment on the text,<note n="t" place="margin">Non deſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rebant Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>videm in tantis ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis ſuae Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, ſed ubi Leonina non prode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat, aſſumit vulpinam. H. Grotius in <hi>2 Sam. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> and ſaith <hi>David</hi> as a great comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and experienced general, wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted neither wit nor arts, and marti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al deſigns, to cruſh in peices, and counterplot <hi>Abſolons</hi> ambitious aimes, others conjecture that this extraordinary command and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, was given to <hi>Huſhai</hi> from <hi>David</hi> as his <hi>King,</hi> who having a ſoveraign power over all his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects might exact obedience, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a ſuperlative Authority, in ſo great a peril to circumſtance his roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al pleaſure in this ſervice: as the King ſhould pleaſe to judge fit for perſons, time and place, and this ſeems very probable from the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Samuel</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">
                  <hi>2 Sam. 15.33.34.</hi> Si veneris mecum eris mihi oneri.</note> who thus records the dialogue betwixt the King and <hi>Huſhai, If thou paſſeſt on with me, thou ſhalt be a burden to me, but if thou return into the City thou maiſt defeat the Counſel of Achitophel.</hi>
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:58102:83"/>And <hi>Vatablus</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Videſne tu? valeſne tu in conci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio, quod ſi vales con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilio rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tere, plus enim mihi profueris redeundo quam ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nendo Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tablus in loc. <hi>2. Sam. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> ſeemeth to encline much to this purpoſe, as if the King had reaſoned<note n="y" place="margin">Nonne videns es? nonne Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheta es? ſi dominus reſponderit tibi redeun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum in ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bem redito, Chal. Paraph.</note> the caſe and debated with <hi>Huſhai,</hi> thus; ſaying, thou art a ſubject of great experience, as ſharp-ſighted as an Eagle in popular com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions, ſtrong in judgement, pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in Counſels, Eloquent and powerful in perſwaſion, a Lion for courage, and a Lamb for courtſhip: civility and curteſie, go thou into the City <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> and if poſſible defeat <hi>Achitophels</hi> counſel; there is a third conjecture, which ſeems to carry with it the cleareſt truth, and that is in this unexemplary com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand and ſervice, King <hi>David</hi> as a Prophet, and the Lords annointed, by a divine direction or infuſion from above in this ſea of troubles, guided more eſpecially by the dictates of Gods holy ſpirit, found out this happy expedient to avoide his Enemies, and to deſtroy their traiterous combinations, this ſeem
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:58102:83"/>to be genuinly derived from the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred hiſtory,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 15.31.</note> which relates that King <hi>David</hi> worſhipping God, fell to his prayers and ſaid<note n="z" place="margin">
                  <hi>2 Sam. 15.34.</hi> Dixeris Abſolom ſervus tuus ſum Rex; Patere me vivere.</note> 
               <hi>O Lord I pray thee turn the counſel of</hi> Achito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phel <hi>into fooliſhneſse,</hi> and the King had no ſooner ended his prayers, and was come to the top of the mount where he worſhipped God but <hi>Huſhai</hi> came to meet him, and the King (as directed by the ſpirit of God) immediately commandeth <hi>Huſhai</hi> inſtructing him with the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and a form of ſuch words, as ſeemed to be ſutable only for ſuch a ſervice, as he was employed in, and as ſent from Heaven to ſave a King from periſhing, and to preſerve a Kingdome a <hi>Say</hi> (Huſhai) <hi>unto</hi> Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolon <hi>I will be thy ſervant O King, as I have been thy Fathers ſervant hitherto, ſo will I now be thy ſervant alſo.</hi> This commiſsion was only ſutable to ſuch a ſoveraign Prince, whoſe divine ſpirit, was directed
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:58102:84"/>from above and it is very colligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble from the context of this ſtory: that King <hi>David</hi> had for the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action of this high concern (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a King, a Church and Kingdome were all in ſuch eminent danger) an extraordinary and prophetical ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and that will plainly manifeſt it<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, when it is obſerved and ſcanned how <hi>Huſhai</hi> comported himſelf in this royal truſt wherein the King em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed him, which was ſo ſuccesful; that (by Gods aſſiſtance) it cauſed the ruine of the traitors and that high rebellion. The Prophet menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons <hi>Huſhai's</hi> inſinuation into <hi>Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lons</hi> preſence, and into his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, wherein as he ſhewed his obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to his Prince and his own matchleſs wiſdome, and invincible courage, who was neither catched with <hi>Abſolons</hi> flattery, nor danted with the oraculous policy of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidious <hi>Achitophel. Huſhai</hi> made his way as King <hi>David</hi> commanded
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:58102:84"/>him, ſaying, to <hi>Abſolon</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">2 Sam. 16.16. <hi>Salve Rex. Salve Rex.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>God ſave the King, God ſave the King:</hi> and now having by fair ſpeeches juſtly inſnared the flatterer, and gained ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance and credulity, <hi>Hushai</hi> at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth his opportunity, to annihi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late and deſtroy the traytors and their treaſon, which he brought to good effect: firſt, by oppoſing and decrying the counſels of <hi>Achito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phel,</hi> which being refuſed, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpairing Statiſt, <hi>went forth and hanged himſelf.</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">2 Sam. 17.25.</note> It cannot but be perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent to obſerve how juſtly the judgements of God found out this prodigious matchiavil; who ſowed the tares of diſſention betwixt a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and his Son: and cheriſhed the ſeeds of Rebellion in the ſubjects againſt their Liege Lord and King: the horror of his crimes, (as yet more odious and abominable in the eyes of God and men) are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded to his laſting infamie in the ſacred Hiſtory, where the diverſity
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:58102:85"/>of <hi>Achitophels</hi> and <hi>Huſhai's</hi> coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels are ſet forth at large, with the ſucceſſe of both. Firſt, <hi>Abſolon</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth for <hi>Achitophel</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">2 Sam. 16.20.</note> 
               <hi>and ſaid give me counſel, what we shall do,</hi> and as he preſently venteth the poyſon of his ſoul, damnably adviſing <hi>Abſolon to go into his Fathers Concubines, which he hath left to keep the houſe, and all</hi> Iſrael <hi>shal hear that thou art abhorred of thy Father, then shall all the hands that are with thee be ſtrong.</hi> This evil counſel was to well entertained and practiſed, and proſecuted with as much impudency as impiety, <hi>So they ſpread</hi> Abſolon <hi>a Tent upon the top of the Houſe, and</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">2 Sam. 16.22.</note> Abſolon <hi>went into his Fathers Concubines in the ſight of all</hi> Iſrael. As this foul ſin was prepared to make not only a breach, but an abhorrency betwixt the Father and the Son, ſo the <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beonite</hi> proceeded in his dangerous and deſtructive counſels perſwading <hi>Abſolon, that he might have the
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:58102:85"/>choice of twelve thouſand men, that he might ariſe and purſue after</hi> Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid <hi>in the night, and ſaith he I will come upon him while he is weary and weakhanded, and will make him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid, and all the people that are with him shall flee, and I will ſmite the King only.</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Sam. 17.1.2.</note> Herein was much miſchief contayned as the force of a conſiderable Army, the terrour of a purſuit in the night, and bloud thirſty cruelty threatning, to chaſe or ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe a feeble and fainty marching Army; and moſt maliciouſly to ſmite and murder the King only, but God prevented the miſchiefs of this bad counſel and fowl deſign. For it pleaſed the providence of Heaven, to order that <hi>Abſolon</hi> ſhould call likewiſe <hi>Hushai</hi> the <hi>Archite</hi> and to hear what he ſaid and he (obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to King <hi>Davids</hi> inſtructions, and guided by the breathings of the holy ſpirit gave counſel) of another complexion, ſaying boldly and
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:58102:86"/>faithfully<note n="f" place="margin">2 Sam. 17.7.</note> 
               <hi>That the counſel that</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chitophel <hi>hath given is not good at this time for</hi> (<hi>ſaid</hi> Huſhai) <hi>thou knoweſt that thy Father and his men be mighty men, and they be chafed in their minds</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Bitter of Soul.</note> 
               <hi>as a bear that is robbed of her whelps in the field, and thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is a man of war and will not lodge with the people behold he is now hid in ſome pit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 17.7.8.9.10.11.</note> 
               <hi>or in ſome other place: And it will come to paſs when ſome of them be overthrown at the firſt, that whoſoever heareth it, will ſay, there is a ſlaughter among the people that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low</hi> Abſolon. <hi>And he alſo that is valiant and his heart as the heart of a Lyon shall utterly melt: for all</hi> Iſrael <hi>know that thy Father is a mighty man and that they that be with him be va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lient men. Therefore I counſel that all</hi> Iſrael <hi>be gathered generally to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from</hi> Dan <hi>even to</hi> Beerſheba, <hi>as the ſand that is by the ſea for multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, and that thou go to battaile in thy own perſon, ſo shall we come upon
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:58102:86"/>him in ſome place where he shall be found, and we will light upon him as the dew that falleth uppon the ground, and of him and of all the men that are with him, there shall not be left ſo much as one. Moreover if he be gotten into a City, then shall all</hi> Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael <hi>bring ropes unto that City and we will draw it into the River, until there be not on ſmall stone to be found there.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This counſel was clean contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to <hi>Achitophels</hi> preſenting King <hi>David</hi> and his Army not feeble but formidable, and admitted not of <hi>Achitophels</hi> but of <hi>Abſolons</hi> own advancing with his Army of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, and as God had appointed and ordered, even ſo it came to paſs.<note n="h" place="margin">2 Sam. 17.14.</note> 
               <hi>And</hi> Abſolon <hi>and all the men of</hi> Iſrael <hi>ſaid, the counſel of</hi> Huſhai <hi>the</hi> Archite <hi>is better then the counſel of</hi> Achitophel. This endeavour ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding proſperouſly, it was to be hoped that the traitors being diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in their counſels, might not
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:58102:87"/>proſper in their black deſign which fell out accordingly. God and the King having inſtructed <hi>Hushai,</hi> the work went on the better and the holy record beareth witneſſe of the truth. <hi>For the Lord had</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">2 Sam. 17.14.</note> 
               <hi>appointed</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Nutu do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini</hi> the original beares had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded</note> 
               <hi>to defeat the good counſel of</hi> Achito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phel: <hi>Vt induceret Dominus malum, ſuper</hi> Abſolon; <hi>to the intent that the Lord might bring evil uppon</hi> Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon. Theſe great tranſactions, thus wiſely &amp; faithfully managed; <hi>Hushai</hi> (according to the Kings command) imparted the ſecrets and reſults of the counſels <hi>to</hi> Zadock <hi>and</hi> Abia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thar <hi>the Prieſts, ſaying, thus and thus did</hi> Achitophel <hi>counſel</hi> Abſolon <hi>and the Elders of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>and thus and thus have I counſelled, now therefore ſend quickly</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">2 Sam. 17.15.16.</note> 
               <hi>and tell</hi> David, <hi>ſaying, lodge not this night in the plaines of the wilderneſs, but ſpeedily paſs over, least the King be ſwallowed up, and all the people that are with him. Now</hi> Ionathan <hi>and</hi> Ahimaaz <hi>ſtayed by</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogel
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:58102:87"/>(<hi>for they might not be ſeen within the City) and a wench went and told them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vers. 22.</note> 
               <hi>and they went and told King</hi> David <hi>and he aroſe</hi> upon this intelligence, <hi>and all the people that were with him and paſſed over</hi> Jordan <hi>by the morning light, there lacked not one of them that was not gone over</hi> Iordan. The King thus adviſed of the Enemies deſignes, advanced to <hi>Mahonaim</hi> and taking a view of his forces, divided his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my into three Brigades, and ſet one third part under the command of his General <hi>Joab,</hi>
               <note place="margin">King <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals <hi>Ioab Aibſhai Ittai.</hi> 2 Sam. 18.2.6.7.</note> another third part under the command <hi>Abishai</hi> the Son of <hi>Zerviah,</hi> and a third patt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the hand of <hi>Ittai</hi> the <hi>Gittite;</hi> the Army then and thus advancing, the battel <hi>was in the wood of</hi> Ephraim <hi>where the people of</hi> Iſrael <hi>were ſlain before the ſervants of</hi> David, <hi>and there was a ſlaughter that day of twenty thouſand men,</hi> and <hi>Abſolon</hi> (as neither worthy of favour from
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:58102:88"/>Heaven or Earth) riding on a mule <hi>his head was caught hold</hi> on by the thick boughes of the Oak, and the Mule, (the very beaſt whereon he rode) forſook him and went away and left him to be pierced through with the darts of vengance, and the weapons of death. The Traitors thus diſperſed and routed, good news of a happy victory,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 18.31.</note> and ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of Salvation was poſted to King <hi>David</hi> in the mouth of <hi>Chushi</hi> 
               <hi rend="sup">n</hi> ſo the Prophet <hi>Samuel</hi> relates that <hi>Chushi</hi> came, and <hi>Chushi</hi> ſaid, <hi>tidings my Lord the King, for the Lord hath avenged thee this day on all thoſe that roſe up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee.</hi> The Enemies diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fited and the victory proclaimed <hi>Iſrael</hi> as well as <hi>Iudah</hi> fell into a zealous emulation and contention for loyalty, and King <hi>Davids</hi> Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies ſtrive to manifeſt themſelves chearſul and obedient ſubjects: this is evident in the ſacred paſſages of
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:58102:88"/>this royal ſtory, Iſrael <hi>fled every man to his tent,</hi> and as at an inſtant in the next verſe ſaith the Prophet <hi>and all the people were at strife,</hi> through all the tribes of <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſaying, <hi>The King ſaved us out of the hands of our Enemies,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 19.6.</note> 
               <hi>and he delivered us out of the</hi> Philiſtines, <hi>and now he is fled out of the Land, for</hi> Abſolon, <hi>and</hi> Abſolon <hi>whom we have anointed over us is dead in battel. Now therefore why ſpeak ye not a word of bringing the King back.</hi> Thus the Kings greateſt Enemies in his ſuddain proſperity became his friends, but as for <hi>Iudah</hi> his loyal party, the King (returning towards <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> in triumph) had an eye principally on them. <hi>And King</hi> David <hi>ſent to</hi> Zadock <hi>and to</hi> Abiathar, <hi>ſaying, ſpeak unto the Elders of</hi> Judah <hi>ſaying, why are ye the laſt to bring back the King to his houſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 19.10.11.</note> 
               <hi>ſeeing the ſpeech of all</hi> Iſrael <hi>is come to the King even to his houſe, ye are my brethren, ye are my bones, and ye are my fleſh, wherefore then are ye the laſt to bring back the King.</hi> Thus at King <hi>Davids</hi> return and
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:58102:89"/>reſtauration towards <hi>Hieruſalem Iudah</hi> and <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 19.15.</note> friends and foes all being King <hi>Davids</hi> ſubjects,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1</hi> Vnanimi conſenſu Tremel in loc</note> uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted their acclamations in this happy occaſion of ſolemn joy:<note place="margin">2 Sam 19.41.42 43.</note> and as ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vals ſeemed to contend whether Tribes ſhould appear more abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute and perfect royaliſts, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets expreſſions are moſt emphati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal. <hi>And behold all the men of</hi> Iſrael <hi>came to the King,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tribules Iehudae &amp; qui pro Davide mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litarant qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus copiis freti auda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciores erant in ſua reſponſione Iunius</note> 
               <hi>and ſaid unto the King, why have our brethren the men of</hi> Iudah <hi>ſtolen thee away, and brought the King and his houſhould &amp; all Davids men with him over</hi> Jordan? <hi>And all the men of</hi> Judah <hi>anſwered the men of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>becauſe the King is near of kin to us, Wherefore then be ye angry for this matter? have we eaten at all of the Kings coſt?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Refellendo rationes Iſraelitaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; ludifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can do co inſolentius adhuc locu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti ſunt, quam Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelitae. Tremel, in loc.</note> 
               <hi>or hath he given us any gift? And the men of</hi> Iſrael <hi>anſwered the men of</hi> Judah, <hi>and ſaid, we have ten parts in the King, &amp; we have alſo more right in</hi> David <hi>then ye, why then did ye deſpiſe us, that our advice ſhould not be firſt had in bringing back our King? and the words of the men of</hi> Judath <hi>were fiercer then the words of the men of</hi> Iſrael.
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:58102:89"/>as juſtly deſpiſing their pretences to merits and thanks who had ſo lately co-aſſiſted in ſuch a bloody rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The ſtorm thus over of King <hi>Davids</hi> troubles, and the confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſo calmed and allayed by the Kings incomparable wiſdome, his Generals courage and conduct in the Army, and the unparaleld coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel and fidelity of <hi>Huſhai,</hi> the King was gloriouſly reſtored to his throne, the Prieſts admitted peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably to attend at the Altar, and all the ſubjects, both <hi>Iudah</hi> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> contended for more exact prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency in the duty of loyalty and allegiance. Theſe were the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ffects of theſe noble endeavours conferring much advantage to the King and Kingdomes happineſſe, &amp; theſe examples of Fidelity and Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty may direct all ſubjects of fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ages to intimate (to their ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt power) the ſincere and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>Iſraelite,</hi> and that none may
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:58102:90" rendition="simple:additions"/>over admire, or too much flatter themſelves or ſervices,<note place="margin">Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions on <hi>Hnſhai,</hi>
               </note> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſ. </seg>I</label> it may prove pertinent and to the purpoſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that <hi>Huſhai</hi> was (firſt) paſſionately afflicted, when he heard of the Kings diſtreſſe and danger, and dutifully attended his royal perſon and commands: (ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly) he ſturred not from the King until <hi>David</hi> commanded him. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>II</label> (thirdly) <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>III</label> that he waited on <hi>Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> in his counſels, but not without the Kings privity and inſtruction: (fourthly) <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>IV</label> that he exceeded not his commiſſion, but from point to point obeyed the Kings pleaſure: (fiftly) <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>V</label> that his confidence and the perſons to whom he was recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended (for the more happy tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions of the great truſt repoſed in him) were <hi>Zadock</hi> and <hi>Abiathar</hi> the Prieſts and their two ſons <hi>Iona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than</hi> and <hi>Ahimaaz</hi> men of piety, fidelity and ſoberneſſe: (ſixtly) <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>VI</label> that <hi>Huſhai</hi> was ſo high in eſteem
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:58102:90"/>with King <hi>David</hi> that he was both by the King and his Enemies, owned as King <hi>Davids</hi> friend, (ſeventhly) <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>VII</label> that the hand of God did ſignally appear (at this time) in the Kings great deliverance and readvance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to his Throne, for God had appointed, and Commanded it ſhould be ſo: Theſe circumſtances premiſed. It will be the ſafeſt way and moſt honourable: for all ſubjects who; (as deluded Iſraelites have offended their Soveraign, and yield<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed either to <hi>Abſolons</hi> flattery or <hi>Achitophels</hi> Counſels, and ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed their ſouls with Treaſon and Rebellion:) to become cordial and true converts to their Prince; and laying faſt hold on his mercy and clemency to repent them truly for their crimes and errours. For this is the plain Path to true Content, and high way, and paſſage to Heaven.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:58102:91"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of a crown</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:58102:91"/>
            <p>The Parallel betwixt King CHARLES the II. <hi>King of</hi> ENGLAND, And LEWIS the IV. <hi>the</hi> FRENCH <hi>King.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:58102:92"/>
            <p>THe Father of King <hi>Lewis</hi> the fourth of <hi>France</hi> was depoſed, and dead in Priſon: his Subjects in Rebellion; and at the ſame time, he an Exile in <hi>England:</hi> but the ſucceſs of time changed the face of all affairs and ſtrook a deep ſence into the Rebels thoughts, ſo that they who ſo evil entreated the Father, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>called the Son to elevate him to the Royal Throne.</p>
            <p>Behold here that Gallant young Prince at the Sea-ſide, and in the view of thoſe Veſſels; wherein he ſailed, from <hi>Dover</hi> to <hi>Calis;</hi> Thus Congratulating his Subjects, before he accepted the preſent of his Scepter.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed firſt. <hi>1654.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Reprinted again. <hi>1659.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="143" facs="tcp:58102:92"/>
            <head>
               <hi>LEWIS the IV.</hi> To his Revolted Subjects.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Efore I ſhall receive your Oath of Fidelity, which I may juſtly demand, and you ought dutifully to take, I ſhall let you know you have recalled (this day) a Prince (who during his Exile) had nothing elſe to doe, but to ſtudy how to Rule and Reign; and hereby I ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force you to believe that you ſhall not be able to make a Royal Throne a paſſage into my Fathers priſon: And after you have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented me with a Crown, to dare to wiſh me ſo much ill, as once to think of Chains and Irons. I know
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:58102:93"/>well, that this diſcourſe will ſurpriſe you, and that you did not believe when you preſented me with a Scepter, that I ſhould not rather have received it with Thanks, then Reprehenſions; but this act is extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary in its commencement, in its progreſs and in its concluſion; and it is juſt that all circumſtances ſhould be proportionable. Let it then ſuffice you onely to know, that if I be ignorant to what point Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects are to pay their obeiſance, yet I am not ignorant to what degree Soveraigns may extend their cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency: Notwithſtanding there is this difference betwixt them, that the <hi>Subjects have no limits for the firſt, but Soveraigns have for the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. The People are obliged to the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces wills, both by their Births &amp; their Lawes. They owe them their goods, their lives and their liberties; and their Princes owe them nothing but Iustice, which can hardly pardon
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:58102:93"/>Traytors.</hi> If theſe Truths &amp; Maximes had been equally underſtood, and followed by the late King my So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign, and you his People, affairs had not been in that ſad condition as they now are. The State had not been reduc'd to ſuch confuſion; the Provinces had not been Cantonized; <hi>Germany</hi> had not been ſo full of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions; <hi>Italy</hi> had not been ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided; all the Cities of the Kingdom had not had ſo many kings as they now have Governours; you had not been guilty of the crime of Treaſon, in elevating an Uſurper to the Throne, the King my Father might ſtill have Reigned, or (at leaſt) I might have received the Crown from his hands, and not from yours; his Tomb might have been bedewed with my tears, his Scepter had not been prophaned, his Hearſe might have been covered with Trophies, &amp; not with Chains.
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:58102:94"/>you might have been <hi>happy and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent.</hi> But as his <hi>Clemency,</hi> and your <hi>Rebellion</hi> were the ſole cauſers of all theſe evils, ſo your <hi>Obedience,</hi> and my <hi>Iustice,</hi> are the only means to make reparation. Conſider a little (I pray you) (that you fall not back in the ſame eſtate wherein you were,) in what Relation you now ſtand; and in what condition I am. Firſt, you have violated all ſorts of Rights in the perſon of your King, you have raiſed a War againſt him; you have aſſaulted him, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards poyſoned him; you have abuſed the confidence he had in you, you have detained him pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner with as great <hi>Treaſon</hi> as <hi>Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice,</hi> with as great <hi>inſolency</hi> as <hi>cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty:</hi> an <hi>injury</hi> which was never of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered (hardly) to the perſon of an ordinary <hi>Herald.</hi> Thus you have violated, and impudently abuſed your <hi>King;</hi> you have detained him priſoner during a Treatie of Peace,
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:58102:94"/>for five years together led him from priſon to priſon; you have forced him not only to ſet by his <hi>Militia</hi> and to depoſe his Crown; but you have conſtrain'd him with violence to transfer it into other hands then to mine. To conclude, you put him to death, and you have reduced my ſelf to a ſtrict neceſſitie, to ſearch my ſafetie in my flight, and to go and ſhew my miſerie beyond the Seas. Yet this is not all, you have done one thing which never any did before, it hath been ſeen ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times that the <hi>Grandees</hi> of a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom have interpoſed themſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a <hi>Tyranny,</hi> and have deſtroyed it; but 'twas never ſeen that they themſelves elevated a <hi>Tyrant</hi> to the Throne as <hi>you</hi> have done: In theſe kind of crimes the Abettors may be ſaid to be more criminal then he who hath received all the fruit: For if each one of you in particular had aſpired to ſet the Crown upon his
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:58102:95"/>own head, you might have been more excuſable, then to have ſnatcht it from your lawfull <hi>Prince</hi> to place it on the head of an <hi>Vſurper.</hi> But you'l ſay to me, <hi>the Prince that bore it was not able to ſupport it.</hi> To that I ſhall anſwer, As I have the honour to be his Son, and was his Subject, it belongeth not to me to determine what he <hi>could,</hi> or what he <hi>could not:</hi> ſeeing he was my <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> I ought not to preſume to be his judge, and ſeeing he was my King, I ought not to be ſo impudent to cenſure, much leſſe to condemn his actions, he being not obliged to render an account to any, <hi>But God alone.</hi> Believe then, the ſame reſpect I have for his memorie, you ought to have had for his perſon, he was your King as well as mine: ſeeing then that <hi>Kings are called the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the people.</hi> Their Subjects are obliged to have for them a true reſentment of a reſpect, which their
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:58102:95"/>very birth may infuſe into them: Beſides, as <hi>Soveraigns are the true Images of God, and that the ſplendor of their puiſſance is abeam and ray of his power;</hi> Subjects ought to have an equal ſubmiſſion to their Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigns will. When you ſee a Comet appear, the Sun eclipſed, the Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der bolt fall on innocent heads, when you ſee Floods drown whole Towns, by their inundation, and the Sea (paſſing his bounds, and ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing whole Provinces in the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of the deep) devour them up: When you ſee an Earthquake make Kingdoms tremble, and cauſe horrid devaſtations of whole Countries, then (I ſay) it is permitted to the People to murmure? Do you not diſcern the contrarie, how in theſe occurrences they redouble their vowes and prayers, and that they are never more obedient to God, then at ſuch a time, as if God had forſaken his providence of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe?
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:58102:96"/>and when it ſhall ſo happen, that Heaven (for the puniſhment of your ſins) gives you a Prince under whoſe Reign <hi>policy</hi> and <hi>prudence</hi> are not well obſerved, during whoſe Government Forraign and Civil Wars devour all with cruell ravages: it belongeth not then to you to reprehend and condemn your Soveraign; for is he feeble? then you ought to ſuſtain him: is he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate? you ought to bemoan him: is he wicked? you ought to look upon him as a ſcourge and chaſtiſement ſent from Heaven, and to wait with Patience for a remedie from that hand, which hath cauſed your evil. For when a Prince com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands an Armie, and gives Battail; if it ſo happen that the Souldiers per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form not their devoirs and dutie, that his ſquadrons yield, the main body be broken, and (in the end after he hath done even miracles in his perſon, he be yet conſtrained to
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:58102:96"/>quit the field, and to retreat from his Enemies? is it not the Prince that loſeth the Battail? Is it not the Prince that ſuffers the diſgrace? Is it not the Prince that is reputed van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſht? And that bears the loſs and infamie of the day? Notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that by his own particular a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions he hath merited to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror? ſeeing it is thus, why will not you (in ſuch conjunctions) bear with the infirmities, &amp; misfortunes of your Princes, as well as they do with yours? Or (to ſpeak ſomething yet nearer to the quick) why doe you not repair theſe diſorders by your own more exact obedience? The Prince alone is obvious in a Battail to the infamie, Cowardiſe and misfortune of his whole Army, and you are thouſands, who are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to ſtrengthen the Authoritie and honour of your King, which he cannot ſupport with his ſingle va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour. Believe me, <hi>if all Subjects
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:58102:97"/>would be loyal, no Kingdome could be miſerable:</hi> and <hi>if all Princes thought more of ſeverity then of Clemencie, there would not be ſo many Subjects; Rebels.</hi> Moreover, if it were permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Capritious people to take and give Crowns, when they fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cied a change: I conceive there is not a Shepheard but might hope to be a King, and not a King but might be reduced to be a Shepheard; ſo unruly and uncertain are their floating judgements. But (to ſpeak the truth to you) theſe things ought not thus to paſs: we are your <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters,</hi> and you ought not to become <hi>ours.</hi> It is not that I am ignorant that <hi>God diſpoſeth of Scepters and Crowns, as he pleaſes, and gives them as he liſts, and beſtowes them on, or takes them from whom he will, and what he alwayes doth is without all injuſtice; ſometimes permitting that the people ſhall elevate to the Throne, thoſe who never pretended to ſuch a
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:58102:97"/>high degree. But when ſuch an acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent happeneth, it is uſually in favour to thoſe extraordinary perſons in whom Virtue hath impreſt a Royal Character ſo viſible, that it were almoſt injuſtice not to admit them Kings.</hi> To conclude, that which precedes, and that which follows, ought to be ſufficient to juſtifie the effect, and it became <hi>Charles, Martel, Pepin,</hi> and <hi>Charlemain</hi> puiſſantly to erect a Throne, which was not founded upon a line of right ſucceſſion, yet even in this re-encounter you will ſee the event to this preſent hath not authorized your deſign; The Engine of this enterprize hath been ſlain in battail: The <hi>Arch-Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Rhemes</hi> preſerved not his life, but three dayes after he had anointed the Uſurper. But it is not ſeaſonable (to day) to exaggerate the injuſtice of your proceedings; I am not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to particularize other things, and I ſhall ſatisfie my ſelf with telling
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:58102:98"/>you, in general, that <hi>Kings ought not to loſe their Crowns, but with their lives, and that nothing can diſpenſe Subjects from the reſpect, and loyalty, which they owe to their Soveraigns, nor any pretence (whatſoever) Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rize Treaſon and Rebellion. If ſacred perſons</hi> may not enjoy their particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar priviledge, <hi>(which is derived from none but God)</hi> they ſhall be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, more then others, to all ſorts of miſeries; Their guards will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to them inſtead of enemies, their Thrones will rather ſeem a direful precipice then a place of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and ſafety; a <hi>King (of this kind)</hi> is no better then an <hi>illuſtrious ſlave,</hi> when he ſhall have as many Maſters as Subjects. This firſt diſorder will quickly cauſe a ſecond, for when the <hi>Nobles</hi> of a Kingdom fail in their duty to their <hi>Prince,</hi> their own <hi>Vaſſals,</hi> and <hi>Tenants</hi> will forfeit their fealtie to them, and then <hi>Rebellion</hi> communicated from the <hi>Grandees</hi>
               <pb n="155" facs="tcp:58102:98"/>to the <hi>Commons,</hi> and ſo deſcending from one Soul to another, an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal confuſion ſwells and devours all. <hi>Every one will command, and no perſon obey,</hi> (and in this reſentment of <hi>Levelling equality</hi>) <hi>each perſon proves a ſlave to his own ambition, &amp; no one, either rationally Commands himſelf or others.</hi> In effect, this is the moſt ſad condition that a Kingdom can fall into, when there is no ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, and where (for their puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) the Prince hath not force to reduce the people to their obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. For mine own part, when I conſider my ſelf to be the Son of a King, the ſucceſſour of ſo many Kings, and yet, notwithſtanding that I immediately ſucceed not my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: This <hi>Idea</hi> imprints in me, a ſtrange confuſion as towards you, and an extream grief as towards my ſelf: for when I reflect how the ſame Subjects who inchained <hi>Charles in Fetters,</hi> and gave the Crown to <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert,</hi>
               <pb n="156" facs="tcp:58102:99"/>placed <hi>Lewis</hi> on the Throne, the malice which they bore to the Father, may it not eaſily fall upon the Son? and may not they fear that the Son will revenge the outrages committed againſt the Father? but yet (may ſome one ſay,) thoſe who have ſearcht after you, and paſs'd the Seas to preſent you with a Scepter, they need not fear that the memory of their ancient injuſtice will ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liege you to puniſh them: They have reaſon rather to believe, that this ſubmiſſion ſhould blot out the memory of the firſt disſervice: It is certain, <hi>in the exact Rule of juſtice, no noble Action ought to paſs without his recompence:</hi> and it is really as true, <hi>That no crime ought to eſcape without his puniſhment.</hi> After all theſe rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, what ought you not to fear? and what not to hope? you have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>called me to the Throne, 'tis true, but if you had not, had you not been as Criminal againſt <hi>Lewis,</hi> as
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:58102:99"/>you had been againſt <hi>Charles?</hi> he who gives to another, that which he hath taken from him, reſtores with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt that which he hath taken, but his reſtoration is not a free pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and he ought not to expect thanks for an Action of that nature. No, it ſufficeth of one puniſh not the firſt, without intending any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence for the ſecond. I may ſay alſo, that you underſtand not right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly all my preſent concernments; for why? becauſe you have not left me ſtill in exile, becauſe you have ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred what juſtly appertained to me, Becauſe you underſtood that I came to re-demand mine own, not with a powerful Army: and (being tired with your crimes and miſeries) you believe you may probably diſarm the furie of Heaven, by this Act of juſtice: No, no, confide not in any of theſe pretences, for if I had not ſtronger conſiderations then theſe, I ſhould commence my Reign with
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:58102:100"/>the puniſhment of your treaſons, I ſhould ſend them to priſon, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained the perſon of my Father, &amp; expoſe them to the moſt cruel tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, who contrived and cauſed his death, with the greatneſs of his mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes. Thoſe black crimes are ſuch which nothing can extermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate; <hi>Repentance and tears from com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon errours, where humane frailty may plead excuſe, and not for Traitors and Rebels, nor for thoſe, who have deſtroyed Thrones and Scepters, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaind Kings, created and protected Tyrants.</hi> Think not then, that by taking an Oath of fidelity (which is your dutie) that I am thereby inga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged not to doe what becomes a King. No, I ſcorn a Throne where I ſhould be a ſlave, and I had rather be obſcured in priſon, as my Father was, then not to Reign as Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign. <hi>Thoſe people with whom Loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is elective forbear not to make their Kings abſolute, becauſe they could
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:58102:100"/>have no pretence of Iuſtice to do other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe:</hi> judge then, if thoſe who hold their Crowns from Heaven ought to acknowledge their ſubjects for their Maſters, &amp; whether they ought not rather to puniſh, or pardon, as beſt agreeth with their pleaſure. In a word, <hi>I find it far more glorious to be a loyal Subject, then to be a King disobeyed.</hi> Prepare then your ſelves to render me all that obedience which you owe me, and (without farther informing you, whether you are to hope more for Clemency or Iuſtice) reſolve your ſelves to an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute ſubmiſſion, I know well ſome peeviſh Polititians will cenſure, that I act not as I ought in this conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, and that I ſhould reflect on former paſſages with ſome ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and gratifie you with Preſents, to encourage you with future hopes, but I preſume my Policy is more generous, and more ſecure then theirs; for if I had ſo perſwaded
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:58102:101"/>you, perhaps you would have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved me to have been more fit to wear my Fathers <hi>Irons</hi> then his <hi>Crown;</hi> and would have more ſuſpected me of weakneſs and diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation, this exceſſive indulgence would give you more of fear, and me leſs of honour and eſtimation: I (being then ſo far from following ſuch Maximes) tell you once more, that I declare my ſelf to be your King. And (without farther capitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation with you) I aſcend the Throne by the ſteps of mine own Authority as Soveraignly, as if not recalled by you at all. Hitherto I have let you know I am not igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant how far the duty of Subjects ought to bend: But moreover, I judge it fit to acquaint you to what degree Soveraign Clemency may extend it ſelf; to this end, that by that reſentment, you may reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly know what to fear, and what to hope. Know then, that <hi>although a
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:58102:101"/>Prince may juſtly puniſh Traytors, he may likewiſe pardon penitent offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, principally then, when he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns his pardon ſhall reclaim inſolen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to obedience, and fidelity:</hi> For, ſeeing Kings are the Fathers of the people, they ought not alwayes to be too ſevere in juſtice; and <hi>ſeeing that a Prince may afford grace and pardon to his enemies, he may with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt ſhew pity and mercy to his own Subjects:</hi> He cannot well pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh them all, but muſt (in part) enfeeble himſelf; nor ſluce out their blood without emptying his own veins; wherefore he ought to ſpare as far as Reaſon and Iuſtice can make the way paſſable. When then a particular accident grows up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a Prince, or State, it may ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice that the heads of ſome chief offendors be ſacrificed to a repara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and that by ſome ſevere exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, others may be inſtructed with exemplary terrour. But ſeeing that
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:58102:102"/>the number of the offendors may prove infinite, and if all ſhould be puniſh't, a deſolation of entire Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces might ſucceed, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently more men be loſt then 15. main Battails could devour, ſo that the piles of dead corps ſhould make mountains, and ſevere execution of revenge cauſe Rivers of bloud: in ſuch conſiderations (I ſay) It may be better to uſe a great example of Clemencie, then of Iuſtice, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard ſomething, rather then to looſe the lives of ſo many miſerable ſouls: and <hi>there cannot be a greater Victory then to vanquiſh ones own paſsion</hi> in ſuch dangerous conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures. Fear not then that I ſhall abuſe my Authority, ſince if I ſhould puniſh all who have offended, I ſhould reduce my Kingdom to a forlorn Deſart: For who is there among you that hath not failed of his duty? Some have done miſchief, others have deſired it, or at leaſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:58102:102"/>it to be acted: ſome have aſſiſted <hi>Robert,</hi> others have directly fought againſt their King: ſome have moſt perfidiouſly laid their hands upon their <hi>Anointed Lord,</hi> &amp; committed a <hi>ſâcred perſon</hi> into pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and others have (at leaſt) for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken him. <hi>The publick good is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text of all things, but Rebellion alone is the mother of that horrid Monſter.</hi> The Nobles agitated (as they did) for their own intereſt, and the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple by their madneſs, and unaviſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſeconded their fury, and put in execution the intention of the Parricides: Your wives and your children are not exempt from theſe crimes, ſeeing (without doubt) they made vowes for their Parents offending, and prayers againſt their Prince. Whereas then I cannot pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh you all, but that I muſt utterly exterminate you; it reſteth at my choice, whether I would become a King without Subjects, or to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:58102:103"/>you out of pure grace and bounty, and not by Obligations. It may be that during your lives you may repent you of your ancient crimes, and become as faithful as you have been diſobedient. But (perhaps you will tell me) as to our ſelves, we have repented formerly before we ſent to you to come, and receive the Scepter which belongs to you. 'Tis true, it may be as you have ſaid, and that I have conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered your Addreſſes to me were to make reparation of what formerly paſſed, and that with thoſe hands you would advance to the Throne his Son whoſe Father you had bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barouſly removed. But (after all) <hi>whoſoever can abandon the path of Virtue to make choice of that Vice, can again embrace that occaſion if preſented.</hi> Wherefore you owe greater obligation to me then I can confidence to you; for had I not reſolved to ſhew Grace and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:58102:103"/>the great number of Nobles which the King of <hi>England,</hi> my Uncle, hath preſented to me to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend my perſon, had not come with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Souldiers; each one of theſe who incircle me have troops at their command: and I would not have received my Fathers Crown but in the head of a victorious Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, in the midſt of a Field covered with dead, and dying men; bedewed with the blood of ten thouſand Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels: I would have been the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querour of my Kingdom, and not have mounted unto the Throne ſupported by the ſame hands who ſnatcht it from my Fathers head. But I call to mind I am your King, as you are alſo my Subjects, and in this relation I can love you yet, as guilty as you are: I can have pitty for your errors, and kindneſs for your obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacy; and I will not put my ſelf into a condition of ſadneſs after the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory: I am then come to you with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:58102:104"/>an Army, to receive what is mine. This Action (without doubt) is hardy, bold, and well deſerveth glory; and is ſufficiently obliging to demerit your acknowledgement in all degrees of fidelity. Before that you were criminous, the Divine &amp; humane right conjured you notto forſake your Prince, but this day a new obligation chaineth you to more ſtrict obedience. It is not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough alone to be faithful, ſo to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie your dutie; but it is your part to blot out the memorie of what is paſt, and to juſtifie what is preſent; you ought not to look on me meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as your King, but as a King of your own choice, as a King who hath pardoned you, as a King who confideth in you, who now is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending his perſon into your hands, and commits the very care of his life to your protection, next to Heaven: Studie then to gratifie ſuch preſſing endearments, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:58102:104"/>not the wrath of Heaven up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon your heads by new rebellions. Thoſe who have examined your by paſt actions, approve not (doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs) that reſolution that I have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to return into <hi>France</hi> as I have done; for (they will tell me) what confidence can you have in thoſe who had no regard to their lawfull Sovereign? They pretend much to deſire your preſence, but their fears exceed their deſires: And it is rather to ſecure your perſon, then to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance your Scepter, that though you are this day recalled, yet as long as your youth continu'd, they ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd you to live in exile, &amp; obeyed <hi>Robert;</hi> but he being dead (at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent) and they ſeeing that you were in a condition to obtain by force that which they now offer, they ſeem to repent, not ſo much regard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your loſs, as themſelves. Behold the reaſons which have here con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted with my reſolution, which
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:58102:105"/>(ſeeing they are not without ſome rational ground) I have not deſiſted to perſwade my ſelf, and that in double choice, whether to make a War with you, or confide in you, I have choſe the latter as more glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, and <hi>I love rather to hazard my perſon then the deſtruction of all my Kingdoms.</hi> Thoſe who taught me the art to Reign have well fore-ſeen the Exigencies to which I am now reduced, and therefore without doubt they took ſo much care to adviſe me what to do in juſtice, and what I might be allowed to doe in Clemencie: Theſe two Virtues ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear as contraries, but are not; they accord eaſily in the heart of a Prince. They mutually give place each one to the other in the Empire of his Soul, according to the divers occaſions which are preſented, for he ought alwayes to abound in Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencie, and he ought not likewiſe to be ever too ſevere with the ſtrict
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:58102:105"/>meaſure of juſtice. <hi>Mercy and juſtice are two excellent Virtues, but Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence ought to imploy them both: And the Princes ſole Will, ought to be the only rule to guide them.</hi> Having then conjured you to an equal confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in me, as I have in you, let an Act of Oblivion paſs, and <hi>let us re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member no more former crimes, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it be to prevent relapſes.</hi> Let us not look on the Tomb of <hi>Charles,</hi> but meerly to bedew it with the tears of tender Repentance: Not to make it an Altar whereupon to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice his Enemies; let us Raze to the ground thoſe horrid Cells which ſerved for his Impriſonments, thereby (if poſſible) to deſtroy the memory, and not to leave a mark or point to poſterity of thoſe black crimes; let us aſcend the Throne with as much ſplendor as if it had never been prophaned, and let us Reign (if poſſible) with more ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:58102:106"/>King my Soveraign did. But do not think I ſhall be able to effect it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the aid and ſuccours of my Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects; deceive not your ſelves, <hi>the valour and prudence of the Prince are not ſufficient of themſelves to make a Kingdom happy:</hi> The Subjects ought to contribute their proportions. The Nobles are to offer their loyal Obedience, and the people to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low their good example, and both degrees ought to be united in vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue: for otherwiſe he who giveth Victory and Maſters Fortune, will approve the virtue of the Prince in puniſhing the vice of the Subjects. <hi>Thoſe who are valiant, do not alwayes gain the Battail; and thoſe who are wiſe, are not alwayes fortunate:</hi> How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever let us place our ſelves in ſuch a capacity, that we may be ſucceſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, though we cannot merit it. See here what your Prince hath ſaid un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, who in Lieu of puniſhing you, hath pardoned you; inſtead of
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:58102:106"/>fighting with you, prepares to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend you; inſtead of being your Enemy, becomes your Conſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, and who by his own birth and your choice, is now your Lord, your Maſter, and your King. Theſe two qualities permit me not to Capitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late farther with you: It ſufficeth that I onely adde this; That I admit you to hope for clemencie, whileſt I Reign, as I wiſh you to fear al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes my juſtice, and beware that you put not your ſelves in a condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to make tryal of the ſecond, or of looſing the former.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="172" facs="tcp:58102:107"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The Cenſure on King</hi> LEWIS the IV. of FRANCE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>. <hi>Iulius Caeſar</hi> did in his youth<note n="a" place="margin">C. Iulius Caeſar quam Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam fuge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret etiam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſcens in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidit in Piratas Cilices: de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſit praedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes vilut que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ignaros cepiſſent; ſeque du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plum dare pollicitus eſt; impera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit illis ut ſilerent nec ſibi dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mienti ob ſtreperent. Stupidos ac barbaros appellabat, cumque riſu minitabatur ſe illos acturum in crucem, quod &amp; perfecit.</note> ſparkle and radiat forth, the beams of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty: who, avoiding the rage of <hi>Sylla,</hi> and then falling into the hands of the <hi>Cilician Pyrats;</hi> contemn'd thoſe barbarous Sea-Rovers: who asking a poor ſum for <hi>Caeſars</hi> Ranſome, francly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed twice as much as they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, and being detained until his Ranſome was paid; boldly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the ſlaves to ſilence: and
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:58102:107"/>not to dare to interrupt their Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners reſt with noiſe. When they vilifyed verſes and orations of <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſars</hi> own Compoſure, he called them dull and ſtupid barbarians; and was ſo incenſed &amp; highly diſpleaſed, that he did threaten the villains with the <hi>Gallows,</hi> which decree and reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, was in a ſhort time, moſt puiſſantly effected. And as <hi>Caeſar;</hi> ſo <hi>Alexander</hi> did ſuffer no thought to riſe from his magnanimous ſoul; but what was truly Great and No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble<note n="b" place="margin">Plutarch. An non hie ſtatimagne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcis indo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandri Magni? cui nihil mediocre ſatis eſſe poſſet? idem in vitâ.</note> It is from the ſtemm, and Root of Royalty, that Princely Actions bud and Germinate; and ſuch an action and endeavour, became <hi>Lewis,</hi> (at this juncture and glorious opportunity,) which did carry with it, much of generoſity, as well as prudence, and did not ſo much ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of fierceneſs and the impetuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of youth: as of the ſage and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Conduct of a truly Generous and magnanimous <hi>Prince.</hi> Yet
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:58102:108"/>ſome may object, and politickly urge, what ſtate, prudence, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelled this young Monarch to ſpeak to his Subjects ſo high, when he was ſo low? and having ſcarce got well on horsback, thus to ſalute his Subjects; who had there Arms in their hands? Rebels, Subjects, who had lately tumbled his Father from the Throne, who had torn the Crown from of his Sacred Head, changed his Scepter into chains, and his Pallace into a priſon? might not this bold entrance to the Throne have rather provoked them to deſperation then obedience? and raiſed a new tempeſt, which could not be appeaſed without much dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty? might not this noiſe have ſerved to awaken them to freſh jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies and fears, which their own prudence ſhould have taught them? Certainly this objection (at the firſt view) ſeems invincible, that <hi>Lewis</hi> did not appear ſo diſcreet and judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:58102:108"/>as his condition required, notwithſtanding he failed not in his kingly craft, for whoſoever ſhall examine this great Action from the bottom, and weigh the arguments maturely, will be convinced of this opinion, and neither con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn the Generoſity, nor the reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of <hi>Lewis</hi> in this eminent action. The Counſels of prudence prove different, according to ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral conjunctures of occaſions, and ought to change their counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances according to the preſent di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities, and important alterations of affairs. And, as hardy and bold reſolutions are not alwayes ſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, ſo neither are timorous and fearfull proceedings ever wiſe and ſafe: that Polititian who trembles, and is not confident, who dares do nothing generouſly and ſtoutly, for fear he may prove too raſh and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderate, ſhall be ſeldome fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, he is too ſpeculative a Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plator,
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:58102:109"/>and proves rarely quick, and active. And whiles he amuſeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with curious Conſiderations, whether he ſhould, or ſhould not undertake the enterpriſe, whether he ſhould ſpeak or be ſilent; be an induſtrious actor, or a dull flegma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick ſpectator, the opportunity (by this time) may be well loſt, the ſtars change their ſituations; Aſpects alter, &amp; ſo the fatal moment, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on depended the good or ill ſucceſs of a grand deſign, ſlip clean away without advantage. The Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher (whom ſome cenſured over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe) found that his tedious doating on too much conſideration brought forth no fruit but folly, and that his moſt ſubtile concluſions were no better then fancies and dreams, of one newly awaked out of ſleep, The Augurs telling an old Captain that the pullets would not eat; he quickly diſcern'd the myſtery, and anſwered, if they would not eat ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:58102:109"/>they drank, they ſhould have their fill, and ſo cauſed them to be flung into the Sea; at which ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons he gave battail to his enemies and gain'd the day, An old ſouldier told his General, that their enemies were twenty times more then they; but he replyed gallantly, and for how many then doſt thou account me? Another told his General that the enemies darted Arrowes like ſhowres of hail; he replyed inſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, 'tis ſo much the better for us, we ſhall fight againſt empty quivers, and but ſhadows of men. The Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy<note n="c" place="margin">Caeſar quum ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ximi Ponti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficis ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem (com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petitore Qu. Catis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo.) ô mater aut inquit, Pontificen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> habebis filium; aut exulem: ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celſa indo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les omniſ que repulſe impatiens. Eraſmus Apo de Caſare. Plutarch, in vita I. Caeſar.</note> of high born Heroes, and low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted peaſants is not the ſame. The mariners diſpute in one faſhion aboard their ſhips, and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders and ſouldiers after another in their Trenches. And as theſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are very diſtinct, and different in their qualities, ſo are they in their
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:58102:110"/>Counſels, and agitations. Thoſe who walk in dangerous precipices ought to march boldly, if they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to paſs ſecurely. And in thoſe attempts, he who ſtayes to meaſure the depth of peril in his way, either will prove ſo fearful as not to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture, or elſe will be in great dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of a ruinous fall. To judge then of the Action of <hi>Lewis</hi> the <hi>fourth,</hi> a man ought to conſider, what this Prince preponderated, how his Fathers gentleneſs and civility was his ruine, that he ſpoke to the ſame Rebels, who had raviſht his Fathers Crown from his head, and deptiv'd his perſon of his liberty: And that by the ſame capricious humour they recall'd the Son: who had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed the father, and leſt that ſore might ranckle and ſwell again, and ſo infect and deſtroy the Son as it had the Father, it concerned him to let them know, that he came now to inherit his Fathers Kingdom, and
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:58102:110"/>not his infirmities: That, though firſt impreſſions may exchange, or obliterate ill humours, yet it is with great hazard and difficulty. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was more important to his purpoſe to ſtrike deeper at the root at firſt, to gain advantages. If <hi>Lewis</hi> his feet had been ſeen to tremble, when he was to aſcend the Throne, he muſt have then diſcovered a ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity to fall again. If he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Crown with a dull and phlegmatick deportment, he had been rather made a King by his <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Maſters</hi> then his <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects,</hi> and he would have unfolded to his people the paſſion of coward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fear, rather then have procured due regard from them. We may conclude then, that this Prince was <hi>wiſe,</hi> in being <hi>ſtout</hi> and <hi>Gallant</hi> in this occaſion, that his Policy was not indiſcreet, and (coping with ſouldiers, and men of armes and valour) his diſcourſe was not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proper,
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:58102:111"/>as containing nothing that might give the ſhock to Soveraign prudence: but rather, on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; what well became the Grandeur, and Majeſty of a King.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:58102:111"/>
            <head>The CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <label>I.</label> SOveraignty, the highest truſt. <hi>Pag. 1</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>II.</label> The duty of Subjects. <hi>p. 3</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>III.</label> Of <hi>Huſhai</hi> and his undertakings. <hi>p. 14</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>IV.</label> Converted Royaliſts duty. <hi>p. 41</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>V.</label> No excuſe, Apology or merit to be pleaded for, by Rebels. <hi>p. 45</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>VI.</label> Of a Promiſe. <hi>p. 53</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>VII.</label> Of a Vow. <hi>p. 54</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>VIII.</label> Of the Proteſtation. <hi>p. 58</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>IX.</label> Of the Covenant. <hi>p. 62</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>X.</label> Of the Engagement. <hi>p. 66</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>XI.</label> Of the Oath of Abjuration. <hi>p. 69</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>XII.</label> The Kings Oath at his Corona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>p. 77</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>XIII.</label> The Arch-Biſhops Homage. <hi>p. 82</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>XV.</label> The Oath of a Chancellour. <hi>p. 83</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:58102:112"/>
               <item>
                  <label>XVI.</label> The Oath of a privy Councel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor. <hi>p. 84</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>XVII.</label> The Oath of a Secretary of State. <hi>p. 85</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>XVIII.</label> The Clergies ſubſcription. <hi>p. 88</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>XIX.</label> The Oath agaist Symony. <hi>p. 91</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>XX.</label> The Oath of Allegiance. <hi>p. 97.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>XXI.</label> The Oath of Supremacy. <hi>p. 99</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>XXII.</label> The nine marks of Traytors. <hi>p. 110</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>XXIII.</label> The nine Characters of true Royaliſts. <hi>p. 116</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>XXIV.</label> The Parallel betwixt King <hi>CHARLES</hi> the ſecond; and King <hi>LEWIS</hi> the fourth of France. <hi>p. 143</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>XXV.</label> The Cenſure on King <hi>Lewis</hi> the fourth of France. <hi>p. 172</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:58102:112"/>
            <head>Errata Emendata.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 1. <hi>lin.</hi> 2. <hi>read</hi> Soveraignty is <hi>p.</hi> 5. <hi>l.</hi> 19. <hi>r.</hi> Scrutiny. <hi>p.</hi> 8. <hi>l.</hi> 25. <hi>r.</hi> decry. <hi>p.</hi> 19. <hi>l.</hi> 20. <hi>r.</hi> oylie. <hi>p.</hi> 31. <hi>l.</hi> 26. <hi>r.</hi> nor death. <hi>p.</hi> 49. <hi>l.</hi> 15. <hi>r.</hi> can. <hi>p.</hi> 51. <hi>l.</hi> 6. <hi>r.</hi> or congruity. <hi>p.</hi> 55. <hi>Greek Cota.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>p.</hi> 56. <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>r.</hi> not, <hi>l.</hi> 20. <hi>r.</hi> ſui <hi>p.</hi> 58. margent. <hi>p.</hi> 59. <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>r.</hi> diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction <hi>p.</hi> 61. <hi>l.</hi> 8. <hi>r.</hi> then. <hi>p.</hi> 66. <hi>l.</hi> 24. <hi>r.</hi> vicious. <hi>p.</hi> 75. <hi>l.</hi> 13 <hi>r.</hi> juramental. <hi>p.</hi> 76. <hi>l.</hi> 10. <hi>r</hi> thoſe. <hi>p.</hi> 76. <hi>l.</hi> 20.<hi>r.</hi> external. <hi>p.</hi> 95. marg. <hi>hanc enim per elimenta. p.</hi> 112. <hi>l.</hi> 6. <hi>r. Pulſ. p.</hi> 138. <hi>l.</hi> 17. <hi>r.</hi> Confidents. <hi>Eviſt Dedicat.</hi> Rear-Admiral for Vice Admiral. Creeping ſervants for creeping ſerpents.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
